=== PAGE 1 ===
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Central Board of Direct Taxes, e-
Filing Project 
 
ITR 1 – Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
 
Version 1.0 
15th May 2026 
 
 
Directorate of Income Tax (Systems) E-2, 
A.R.A. Centre, Ground Floor, 
Jhandewalan Extension 
New Delhi – 110055 

=== PAGE 2 ===
Page 2 
 
 
Contents 
Purpose ............................................................................................................................................................. 4 
1 Validation Rules ......................................................................................................................................... 4 
1.1 
Category A: ................................................................................................................................... 5 
1.2 
Category B: ................................................................................................................................. 22 
1.3 
Category D:................................................................................................................................. 22 
 
 
 
 

=== PAGE 3 ===
Page 3 
 
 
List of Tables 
Table 1: List of Category of Defect ........................................................................... 4 
Table 2: Category A Rules ....................................................................................... 5 
Table 3: Category B Rules ......................................................................................22 
Table 4: Category D Rules……………………………………………………………..………..22 
 
  

=== PAGE 4 ===
Page 4 
 
 
Purpose 
The Income Tax Department has provided free return preparation software in downloads 
page which are fully compliant with data quality requirements. However, there are certain 
commercially available software or websites that offer return preparation facilities as well. In 
order to ensure the data quality of ITRs prepared through such commercially available 
software, various types of validation rules are being deployed in the e-Filing portal, so that the 
data which is being uploaded are accurate and compliant to the validation rules to a large 
extent. The taxpayers are advised to review these validation rules to ensure that the 
software used by them is compliant with these requirements, to avoid rejection of return 
due to poor data quality or mistakes in the return. 
 
The software providers are strictly advised to adhere to these rules to avoid inconvenience to 
the taxpayers, who may use their software. Software providers may please note that these 
validation rules will be strictly monitored and enforced, and each rule will have to be 
complied strictly. In case of violations, the concerned return preparation utility/ software is 
liable to be blacklisted without any notice, and such blacklisting will be published on the e-
filing website. No return using blacklisted software will be permitted to be uploaded till the 
time the software provider is able to provide details of correction in software. This may 
cause avoidable inconvenience to the taxpayers and loss of reputation to software providers 
for which the Income Tax Department will not be responsible. 
 
Note- If taxpayer is opting for old tax regime, the return should be filed within due date. 
 
 
1 Validation Rules 
 
The validation process at e-Filing/CPC end is to be carried out in ITR1 for each defect as 
categorized below: 
 
Table 1: List of Category of Defect 
Category of 
defect 
Action to be Taken 
A 
Return will not be allowed to be uploaded. Error message will be displayed. 
B 
Return data will be allowed to be uploaded but the taxpayer uploading the 
return will be informed of a possible defect present in the return u/s 139(9). 
Appropriate notices/ communications will be issued from CPC. 
D 
Return data will be allowed to be uploaded but the taxpayer uploading the 
return will be informed of a possibility of some of the deduction or claim not 
to be allowed or entertained unless the return is accompanied by the 
respective claim forms or particulars. 

=== PAGE 5 ===
Page 5 
 
 
1.1 
Category A: 
Table 2: Category A Rules 
Sl no. 
Publishing Document 
1.  
If Old Tax Regime is selected and Sum of deductions claimed u/s 80C, 80CCC & 80CCD 
(1) cannot be more than Rs. 1,50,000. 
2.  
If Old Tax is selected and employer category is "CG-Pensioners" 
"SG-Pensioners"  
"PSU-Pensioners"   
"Other Pensioners” or Not Applicable, then Deduction u/s 80CCD (1) should not be more 
than 20% of Gross total Income 
3.  
If Old Tax is selected and If the employer category is other than "CG-Pensioners" 
"SG-Pensioners"  
"PSU-Pensioners"   
"Other Pensioners” or Not applicable, then Maximum amount that can be claimed for u/s 
80CCD (1) is 10% of Salary  
4.  
Deduction u/s 80CCD (2) should not be more than 10% of salary by an employer other 
than Central Government or State Government in case of Old tax regime. 
5.  
If Old tax Regime is selected, and 80DDB - Resident assessee has claimed more than the 
maximum limit of Rs.1,00,000/-', 
6.  
If Old tax Regime is selected and Assessee is claiming deduction under section 80DDB, 
but eligible category description not provided 
7.  
 If Old tax Regime is selected, then Maximum amount that can be claimed for category 
"Self or Dependent" u/s 80DDB is Rs. 40,000 
8.  
If Old tax Regime is selected and Deduction u/s 80G claimed but details are not provided 
in Schedule 80G 
9.  
If Old tax Regime is selected, then In Schedule 80G, in Table F, Donation should be equal 
to sum of donation entitled for 100% deduction without qualifying limit + donation entitled 
for 50% without qualifying limit +donation entitled for 100% deduction subject to 
qualifying limit + donation entitled for 50% subject to qualifying limit  
10.  
If Old tax Regime is selected, then In Schedule VIA, deduction claimed u/s 80G is more 
than the eligible amount of donation mentioned in Schedule 80G 
 
11.  
If Old tax Regime is selected, then Assessee can claim deduction under section 80TTA to 
the maximum limit of Rs.10,000/- 
12.  
If Old tax Regime is selected, then Deduction u/s 80TTA is restricted to the savings 
account interest income from other sources.  
13.  
Deduction u/s 80TTA cannot be claimed by Senior Citizen (date of birth is on or Before 
01.04.1966 
14.  
If Old tax Regime is selected, then Assessee can claim deduction under section 80TTB to 
the maximum limit of Rs.50,000/- 
15.  
Assessee being less than 60 years of age cannot claim deduction under section 80TTB 
(date of birth is before 02.04.1966) 
16.  
If Old tax Regime is selected, and Assessee being senior citizen and claiming deduction 
under section 80TTB on other than interest income from other source 
17.  
Total of chapter VI-A deductions should match with sum of individual deductions 
restricted to GTI 

=== PAGE 6 ===
Page 6 
 
 
18.  
Deductions claimed under Chapter VI-A is should not be more than “Gross Total Income” 
19.  
ITR-1 -"Name" of taxpayer in ITR does not match with the "Name" as per the PAN data 
base (This will be verified at the time of upload. To ensure that the name entered is as 
appearing in the PAN card) 
20.  
In the return filed "Gross Total Income" and all the heads of income is entered should be 
more than zero if tax liability has been computed and paid 
21.  
"Income details" and "Tax computation" should be disclosed where details regarding 
“Taxes Paid” have been disclosed. 
22.  
If Old Tax Regime is selected   and Gross Total Income is not equal to the Total of 
Incomes from Salary, House Property & Other Sources & Long-term capital gains as per 
sec 112A. 
23.  
If Old tax Regime is selected, Rebate u/s 87A is claimed by Resident Individual having 
Total income including LTCG 7a(iii) u/s 112A of more than Rs. 5,00,000 
24.  
Total income should be the difference between "Gross total income" and "Total 
deductions" OR Zero if the gross total income minus deduction is negative 
25.  
The amount of "Tax after Rebate " should be equal to "Tax payable on total income" 
Minus "Rebate u/s 87A" 
26.  
The amount at “Total tax and Cess” should be equal to sum of "Tax after Rebate" and 
“Heath & Education Cess 
27.  
“Total Tax, Fees & Interest” should be equal to the sum of“Total Tax & Cess + Interest u/s 
234A + 234B+ 234C + Fees u/s 234-I + 234F- Relief u/s 89” 
28.  
In "Schedule Income Details" Total Interest, Fee Payable should be equal to the sum of 
Interest u/s 234 A+ Interest u/s 234 B+ Interest u/s 234 C+ Fee u/s 234F + Fees u/s 234-I 
29.  
Agriculture Income shown as exempt cannot be more than Rs 5000/- 
30.  
In "schedule "Income Details” Exempt income should be equal to sum of amount entered 
in individual col. Of exempt income. 
31.  
Sec 10(10BC)-Any amount from the Central/State Govt./local authority by way of 
compensation on account of any disaster drop-down cannot be selected more than one time 
under Exempt Income. 
32.  
Sec 10(10D)- Any sum received under a life insurance policy, including the sum allocated 
by way of bonus on such policy except sum as mentioned in sub-clause (a) to (d) of 
Sec.10(10D)" drop-down cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
33.  
Sec 10(11)-Statutory Provident Fund received drop-down cannot be selected more than one 
time under Exempt Income. 
34.  
Sec 10(12)-Recognized Provident Fund received drop-down cannot be selected more than 
one time under Exempt Income. 
35.  
Sec 10(13)-Approved superannuation fund received drop-down cannot be selected more 
than one time under Exempt Income. 
36.  
Sec 10(16)-Scholarships granted to meet the cost of education drop-down cannot be 
selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
37.  
 
If Old Tax Regime is selected; 
 then Sec 10(17)-Allowance MP/MLA/MLC drop-down cannot be selected more than one 
time under Exempt Allowances under salary schedule. 
38.  
Sec 10(18)-Pension received by winner of “PARAM Vir Chakra or "Maha Vir Chakra" or 
"Vir Chakra" or such other gallantry award" drop-down cannot be selected more than one 
time under Exempt Income. 

=== PAGE 7 ===
Page 7 
 
 
39.  
Defense Medical Disability Pension drop-down cannot be selected more than one time 
under Exempt Income. 
40.  
Sec 10(19)-Armed Forces Family pension in case of death during operational duty drop-
down cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt Income 
41.  
Sec 10(26)-Any income as referred to in section 10(26) drop-down cannot be selected 
more than one time under Exempt Income. (Message to be shown to the taxpayers while 
preparing the return that this deduction is available only for certain category of assesses of 
NE Region and Ladakh) 
42.  
Sec 10(26AAA)-Any income as referred to in section 10(26AAA) drop-down cannot be 
selected more than one time under Exempt Income. (Message to be shown to the taxpayers 
while preparing the return that this deduction is available only for certain Sikkimese 
assessees) 
43.  
Standard deduction allowed on House property should be equal to 30% of Annual value. 
44.  
Gross rent received/ receivable/ lettable value should be more than zero or null where 
assessee is claiming municipal tax 
45.  
Taxpayer has selected type of property as let-out or deemed let out then Gross rent 
received/ receivable/ lettable value should be more than zero  
46.  
In Schedule Gross Total Income, Sl.no B2iii. Annual Value should be output of SL.no B2i-
B2ii 
47.  
In Schedule Gross total Income, Sl.no B2vii.Income chargeable under the head ‘House 
Property’ (iii – iv-v + vi) should be equal to sum of B2iii- B2iv-B2v+B2vi or the sum of 
Individual values under the head of House Property cannot be different from the "Income 
chargeable under the head House Property".   
48.  
If Old Tax Regime is selected then In Schedule HP, if "Type of House Property" is 
selected as "Self-Occupied", then the assessee cannot claim interest on borrowed capital 
more than Rs 2,00,000. 
49.  
In "Schedule Income Details" Tax paid to local authorities shall not be allowed for Type of 
House Property as "Self-Occupied" 
50.  
"Interest from savings account" drop-down cannot be selected more than one time under 
Income from other sources 
51.  
"Interest from Deposits (Bank/Post Office/Cooperative Society)" drop-down cannot be 
selected more than one time under Income from other sources 
52.  
In schedule "Income Details” Income from other sources should be equal to sum of 
amounts entered in individual col. of income from other sources 
53.  
In "Schedule Income Details" Deduction u/s 57(iia) shall be allowed only if "Family 
pension" is offered to tax and option 'No' is selected for 'Are you opting for new tax regime 
u/s 115BAC?  
54.  
In case of "Old Tax Regime"- 
Deduction u/s 57(iia) cannot be more than lower of 1/3rd of Family pension or Rs. 15,000. 
 
Note: Rounding off +1 and -1. 
55.  
Interest from Income Tax Refund drop-down cannot be selected more than one time under 
Income from other sources. 
56.  
Family pension drop-down cannot be selected more than one time under Income from 
other sources. 
57.  
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then for Central and State Govt, PSU employees, the 
Entertainment allowance u/s 16(ii) will be allowed to the extent of Rs 5000 or 1/5th of 
Salary whichever is lower 

=== PAGE 8 ===
Page 8 
 
 
58.  
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then No Entertainment allowance u/s 16(ii) will be allowed 
to employees other than Central, State Government and PSU 
59.  
Gross salary should be total of salary as per section 17(1) and value of perquisites as per 
section 17(2) and profits in lieu of salary as per section 17(3)  
60.  
In the Schedule “Gross total Income", 'Net Salary' should be the difference between 'Gross 
salary' and 'Allowances to the extent exempt u/s 10'  
61.  
In Schedule Gross Total Income, B1 (iv) Deductions u/s 16 should be sum of B1 
(iva+ivb+ivc) 
62.  
In Schedule Gross Total Income, Sl.no B1v Income chargeable under Salaries should be 
(B1iii– B1iv) 
63.  
“Total of all allowances to the extent exempt u/s 10 cannot be more than Gross Salary'' 
64.  
If Old Tax Regime is selcted, then Exemption u/Sec 10(5)- Leave Travel 
concession/assistance cannot be more  than respective income in Salary as per section 
17(1) 
65.  
Exempt allowance Sec 10(6)-Remuneration received as an official, by whatever name 
called, of an embassy, high commission etc." cannot be more than Gross Salary 
66.  
Exempt allowance u/s 10(7)-Allowances or perquisites paid or allowed as such outside 
India by the Government to a citizen of India for rendering service outside India cannot be 
more than Gross salary 
67.  
Exempt allowance u/s 10(10)-Death-cum-retirement gratuity received cannot be more than 
Rs. 20,00,000 if nature of employment is  Public Sector Undertaking, PSU - Pensioners, 
others - Pensioners, Others 
68.  
 Exempt Allowance u/s Sec 10(10A)-Commuted value of pension received cannot be more 
than Salary as per sec 17(1) 
69.  
 Exempt Allowance u/s 10(10AA)-Earned leave encashment on retirement cannot more 
than Salary as per sec 17(1) (Message to be shown to the tax payers while preparing the 
return that maximum deduction for a non- Government employees including PSU 
employee is only Rs 25 lakh) 
70.  
 Exempt Allowance u/s 10(10B)-First Proviso- Compensation limit notified by CG in the 
Official Gazette cannot exceed Rs.500,000 
71.  
 Exempt Allowance u/s 10(10C)-Amount received/receivable on voluntary retirement or 
termination of service cannot exceed Rs. 5,00,000 
72.  
In exempt allowances only Sec 10(10B) (i) OR Sec 10(10B) (ii) OR Sec 10(10C) can be 
selected. 
73.  
Exempt Allowance u/s 10(10CC)-Tax paid by employer on non-monetary perquisite 
cannot be more than Value of perquisites as per section 17(2) 
74.  
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then Exempt Allowance Sec 10(13A)-Allowance to meet 
expenditure incurred on house rent cannot be more than Salary as per section 17(1) 
75.  
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then Exempt Allowances -Sec 10(14)(i) Prescribed 
Allowances or benefits (not in a nature of perquisite) specifically granted to meet expenses 
wholly, necessarily and exclusively and to the extent actually incurred, in performance of 
duties of office or employment cannot be more than Value of Salary as per section 17(1) at 
sr. no B1(ia) 
76.  
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then Exempt Allowance -Sec 10(14)(ii) Prescribed 
Allowances or benefits granted to meet personal expenses in performance of duties of 
office or employment or to compensate him for increased cost of living cannot be more 
than Value of Salary as per section 17(1) at sr no (ia) 

=== PAGE 9 ===
Page 9 
 
 
77.  
In Schedule "Income Details" allowance to extent exempt u/s 10 should be equal to sum of 
individual values entered. 
78.  
In Sch 80G Donee PAN should not be same as "Assessee PAN" or "PAN at Verification" 
79.  
In Schedule 80G in table (A) "Donations entitled for 100% deduction without qualifying 
limit" donation in cash or donation in other mode is to be entered mandatory without which 
total deduction column should not be entered 
80.  
In Schedule 80G in table (B) "Donations entitled for 50% deduction without qualifying 
limit" donation in cash or donation in other mode is to be entered mandatory without which 
total deduction column should not be entered 
81.  
In Schedule 80G in table (c) "Donations entitled for 100% deduction Subject to Qualifying 
Limit" Donation in cash or Donation in other mode is to be entered mandatory without 
which total deduction column should not be entered 
82.  
In Schedule 80G in table (D) “Donations entitled for 50% deduction Subject to Qualifying 
Limit" Donation in cash or Donation in other mode is to be entered mandatory without 
which total deduction column should not be entered 
83.  
In Schedule 80G in table (E) Donations should be equal to the sum of (Donations entitled 
for 100% deduction without qualifying limit +Donations entitled for 50% deduction 
without qualifying limit+ Donations entitled for 100% deduction subject to qualifying limit 
+Donations entitled for 100% deduction subject to qualifying limit) 
84.  
Total Donation should be equal to sum of "Donation in cash" AND "Donation in other 
mode" in table (80G) (A)"Donations entitled for 100% deduction without qualifying limit" 
85.  
Total Donation' should be equal to sum of "Donation in cash" AND "Donation in other 
mode" in table (80G) (B)"Donations entitled for 50% deduction without qualifying limit" 
86.  
Total Donation' should be equal to sum of "Donation in cash" AND "Donation in other 
mode" in table (80G) (C)"Donations entitled for 100% deduction subject to qualifying 
limit" 
87.  
Total Donation' should be equal to sum of "Donation in cash" AND "Donation in other 
mode" in table (80G) (D)"Donations entitled for 50% deduction subject to qualifying limit" 
88.  
If Old Tax Regime is selected, and In "schedule 80G" if multiple entries are under donation 
in cash with same PAN then more than Rs 2,000 then amount entered in donation in cash 
will not be considered for calculation of Eligible amount of donation.if sum of all such 
cash donation exceeds Rs. 2000 then eligible amount of donation shall not be more than 0 
or in case of individual entry is more than Rs. 2000 in  
89.  
In "Schedule 80GGA" "Donation in cash" or "Donation in other mode" is to be entered 
mandatory without which total deduction column should not be entered 
90.  
Total Donation' should be equal to sum of "Donation in cash" AND "Donation in other 
mode" in table (80GGA) 
91.  
If Deduction u/s 80GGA is claimed, details should be provided in Schedule 80GGA. 
92.  
In Schedule 80GGA, 'Eligible amount of Donations' cannot be more than the 'Total 
Donations'. 
93.  
In Schedule VIA, deduction claimed u/s 80GGA cannot be more than the eligible amount 
of donation mentioned in Schedule 80GGA 
94.  
Donee PAN mentioned in Schedule 80GGA cannot be same as the assessee PAN or the 
verification PAN 
95.  
In Schedule IT total of col 4 Tax Paid should be equal to sum of individual values 
96.  
In Schedule TCS, “The Amount of TCS claimed this year” should not be more than “Tax 
collected”. 

=== PAGE 10 ===
Page 10 
 
 
97.  
In Schedule TCS total of col 6 TCS credit out of (5) being claimed this year should be 
equal to sum of individual values 
98.  
In Schedule TDS2 (Other than salary), “The Amount of TDS claimed this year” should not 
be more than “Tax deducted”. 
99.  
In Schedule TDS (2), TDS (3)/TCS year of tax deduction cannot be '0' / 'null ' if there is a 
claim of TDS / TCS 
100. 
In Schedule TDS1 total of col 5 'Total Tax deducted" should be equal to sum of individual 
values of col 5 
101. 
In Schedule TDS2 total of col 6 'TDS Credit out of (5) claimed this year" should be equal 
to sum of individual values of col 6 
102. 
In Schedule TDS3 total of col 7' 'TDS Credit out of (5) claimed this year should be equal to 
sum of individual values of col 7 
103. 
TDS, TCS or Tax paid claimed in “Taxes Paid and Verification” should be equal to the 
details of tax amount paid provided in Schedule IT, Schedule TDS1, Schedule TDS2 and 
Schedule TCS.  
104. 
The sum of amounts claimed at TDS, TCS, Advance Tax and Self-Assessment Tax should 
be equal to the amount claimed at “Total Taxes Paid”. 
105. 
Refund claimed should be equal to “Total Taxes Paid” minus “Total Tax and Interest 
payable”. 
106. 
Tax payable Amount should be equal to “Total Tax and Interest payable” minus “Total 
Taxes Paid”. 
107. 
IFSC under “Bank Details” Schedule 80G and in schedule 80GGC should match with the 
RBI database / GIFT IFSC codes. 
108. 
In "Schedule Taxes Paid and Verification" Total TDS Claimed should be equal to the sum 
of total TDS claimed in TDS 1, 2 & 3 
109. 
In "Schedule Taxes Paid and Verification" Total TCS Claimed should be equal to the sum 
of total TCS claimed in TCS schedule 
110. 
In "Schedule Taxes Paid and Verification" Total Advance Tax paid is not equal to the sum 
of total Tax Paid in schedule IT where date of deposit is between 1/04/20XX and 
31/03/20XX of PY for which return is being filed.  
111. 
In "Schedule Taxes Paid and Verification" Total Self-Assessment Tax Paid is not equal to 
the sum of total Tax Paid in schedule IT where date of deposit is after 31/03/20XX of AY 
for which return is being filed. 
112. 
In case of Old Tax Regime, 
taxpayer being an employee can claim Standard deduction u/s 16ia only to the extent of Rs 
50000. 
113. 
Credit for TDS has been claimed in the return of income, but the corresponding 
receipts/income has been omitted to be offered for taxation. (Receipts/ Income should be 
offered to tax in one or the schedules in the return. Further, receipts as appearing in Form 
26AS to be offered to tax in one or the schedules in the return) 
114. 
In Schedule Income Details, the maximum limit allowable under section 80GG is: 
Rs.60,000/- or 25% of his total income excluding LTCG before allowing deduction of this 
expenditure, whichever is less. 
115. 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then the maximum limit allowable under section 
80CCD(1B) is Rs.50,000/- 
116. 
Deduction u/s 80CCD (2) cannot be claimed by taxpayer who has selected employer 
category as "CG-Pensioners" 
"SG-Pensioners"  
"PSU-Pensioners"   

=== PAGE 11 ===
Page 11 
 
 
"Other Pensioners " or "Not Applicable"  
117. 
Total income excluding LTCG C3 (a)(iii) should not be greater than Rs 50 lakhs. 
118. 
In schedule 80GGA, if donation is made in cash same PAN of Donee cannot appear more 
than once 
119. 
House rent allowance (HRA u/s.10(13A)) is claimed, hence deduction u/s.80GG is not 
allowed for the corresponding period.  
120. 
In case of Old Tax Regime - Deduction u/s 80CCD (2) should not be more than 14% of 
salary if any of the employer category is Central Government or state government 
121. 
 If Old Tax Regime is selected, then Assessee claiming deduction u/s 80EE more than the 
maximum limit of Rs 50000/- 
122. 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then Assessee claiming deduction u/s 80EEA more than the 
maximum limit of Rs 150000/- 
123. 
Only one of the deductions u/s 80EE/ 80EEA is allowed. Thus, if deductions claimed 
under section 80EEA is greater than “Zero" deductions claimed under section 80EE cannot 
be greater than “Zero" 
124. 
 If Old Tax Regime is selected, then Assessee claiming deduction u/s 80EEB cannot be 
more than Rs 150000/- 
125. 
Relief u/s 89 cannot be claimed by taxpayer if details of salary as per 17(1), Value of 
perquisite as per 17(2) and Profit in lieu of salary as per 17(3) or family pension are "zero"/ 
"blank" 
126. 
If the original return is filed under section 142(1) then taxpayer cannot file a return u/s 139 
(Will be checked at upload level) 
127. 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then In Schedule 80D, Deduction at Sl. No. 1a Self and 
Family will be allowed to the extent of Rs.25000 
128. 
In Schedule 80D, Deduction at Sl. No. 1a should be equal to sum of Sl. No (i+ii)  
 
Note: This validation to be checked if value of (i+ii) at Sl. No. 1a is less than 25000 
129. 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then In Schedule 80D, the amount of preventive health 
checkup of all the fields combined together should not exceed 5000. 
130. 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then In Schedule 80D, Deduction at Sl. No. 1b Self and 
Family (Senior Citizen) will be allowed to the extent of Rs. 50000 
131. 
In Schedule 80D, Deduction at Sl. No. 1b should be equal to sum of Sl. No (i+ii+iii) Note: 
This validation to be checked if value of (i+ii+iii) at Sl. No. 1b is less than 50000 
132. 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then In Schedule 80D, Deduction at Sl. No. 2a Parents will 
be allowed to the extent of Rs. 25000 
133. 
In Schedule 80D, Deduction at Sl. No. 2a should be equal to sum of Sl. No (i+ii) 
 
Note: This rule will be applicable If Old Tax Regime is selected.  
 
Note: If sum is greater than 25000, then 2a should be restricted to 25000 
134. 
If Old Tax Regime is selected and In Schedule 80D, value at field 2b is greater than Rs. 
50000 
135. 
In Schedule 80D, Deduction at Sl. No. 2b should be equal to sum of Sl. No (i+ii+iii) 
Note: This validation to be checked if value of (i+ii+iii) Sl. No. 2b is less than 50000 

=== PAGE 12 ===
Page 12 
 
 
136. 
If Old tax Regime is selected and In Schedule 80D, Sl. No. 3 Eligible amount of deduction 
is greater than Rs. 100000 
137. 
In Schedule 80D, Eligible amount of deduction at Sl. No. 3 should be equal to sum of Sl. 
No (1a+1b+2a+2b) subject to GTI Note: This validation to be checked if value of Sl. No. 
(1a+1b+2a+2b) at Sl. No. 3 is less than or equal to 100000 
138. 
If 80D claimed in Income Details Deduction under Chapter VIA, then same amount and 
details should be provided in Schedule 80D 
139. 
In Schedule 80G, 'Eligible amount of Donations' cannot be more than the 'Total Donations'. 
140. 
In "Schedule Income Details " Total Tax, Fee & Interest should be equal to sum of Balance 
Tax after Relief +Total Interest, Fee Payable  
141. 
"Sec 10(17A)-Award instituted by Government" drop-down cannot be selected more than 
one time under Exempt Income. 
142. 
If exempt allowance is claimed u/s. 10(10AA) above Rs.25 Lakhs for employer category 
other "Central and state government, CG- Pensioners, SG- Pensioner" 
143. 
Deduction u/s 80GGA is not allowed for donation made in cash above Rs. 2000/-.  
144. 
In schedule 80GGA, if donation is made, same PAN of Donee cannot appear more than 
once 
145. 
In income details total of Dividend income should be equal to sum of “Quarterly breakup 
of Dividend Income"  
146. 
If option Yes is selected for 'Are you opting for new tax regime u/s 115BAC?' then Part C 
– Deductions and Taxable Total Income, Deduction at B5(a), B5(b), B5(c ), 
B5(d),B5(f),B5(g),B5(h),B5(i),B5(j),B5(k),B5(l),B5(m),B5(n),B5(o),B5(p),B5(q),B5(r),B5
(s) should not be more than "0" 
147. 
In schedule 80G, If PAN is already entered in anyone of the set of blocks (i.e. 100%, 50%, 
with Qualifying limit, without Qualifying limit) then same PAN cannot be entered in any 
other block 
148. 
 If New Tax Regime is selected, exempt allowance under Section 10(14)(ii) - “Transport 
allowance granted to certain physically handicapped assessee" should not exceed Rs 
38,400 
149. 
If New Tax Regime is selected and  Exempt allowances under 
"Sec 10(5)-Leave Travel concession/assistance" 
"Sec 10(13A)-Allowance to meet expenditure incurred on house rent" 
"Sec 10(14)(i)- Prescribed Allowances or benefits (not in a nature of perquisite) 
specifically granted to meet expenses wholly, necessarily and exclusively and to the extent 
actually incurred, in performance of duties of office or employment" 
"Sec 10(14)(ii) -Prescribed Allowances or benefits granted to meet personal expenses in 
performance of duties of office or employment or to compensate him for increased cost of 
living" 
 is more than "0" 
150. 
 If Old Tax Regime is selected and Exempt allowances under 
"Section 10(14)(i) - Allowances referred in sub-clauses (a) to (c) of sub-rule (1) in Rule 
2BB" 
"Section 10(14)(ii) - Transport allowance granted to certain physically handicapped 
assessee" 
 is more than "0" 
151. 
Old Tax Regime cannot be selected after the due date of filing of return mentioned u/s 
139(1) 
152. 
Once a proceeding is initiated u/s148, no other return can be filed u/s 139 (Will be blocked 
at upload level) 

=== PAGE 13 ===
Page 13 
 
 
153. 
If New Tax Regime is selected and the Sum of deductions claimed u/s 80C, 80CCC & 
80CCD (1) should not be more than zero. 
154. 
If New tax Regime is selected then In Schedule VIA, deduction claimed   u/s 80DD should 
not be more than "0" 
155. 
If New Tax regime is selected, then deduction claimed u/s 80DDB should not be more than 
"0" 
156. 
If New Tax Regime is selected, then deduction u/s 80G claimed should not be more than 
"0". Further, no details should not be provided in schedule 80G  
157. 
If New Tax Regime is selected 
Then In Schedule VIA, the deduction claimed u/s 80TTA should not be more than "0" 
158. 
If New tax Regime is selected 
Then In Schedule VIA, deduction claimed u/s 80TTB should not be more than "0" 
159. 
If New tax Regime is selected  
Then In Schedule VIA, deduction claimed u/s 80U should not be more than "0" 
160. 
If New tax Regime is selected Then in case of house property loss, Gross Total Income 
should be equal to the Total of Incomes from Salary and Other Sources. 
161. 
If New Tax Regime is selected, then exempt allowance income u/s 10(17)-Allowance 
MP/MLA/MLC should not be more than Zero 
162. 
 If New Tax Regime is selected 
and In Schedule HP, if "Type of House Property" is selected as "Self-Occupied”,  then the 
interest on borrowed capital should not be more than "0”, 
163. 
If New Tax Regime is selected, 
then Entertainment allowance u/s 16(ii) should not be more than "0" 
164. 
If New Tax Regime is selected, 
Then Exemption u/Sec 10(5)- Leave Travel concession/assistance should not be more than 
"0" 
165. 
If New Tax Regime is selected, 
Then Exempt Allowance Sec 10(13A)-Allowance to meet expenditure incurred on house 
rent should not be more than "0" 
166. 
If New Tax Regime is selected 
Then Exempt Allowances -Sec 10(14)(i) Prescribed Allowances or benefits (not in a nature 
of perquisite) specifically granted to meet expenses wholly, necessarily and exclusively 
and to the extent actually incurred, in performance of duties of office or employment 
should not be more than "0" 
167. 
 If New Tax Regime is selected, 
Then Exempt Allowance -Sec 10(14)(ii) Prescribed Allowances or benefits granted to meet 
personal expenses in performance of duties of office or employment or to compensate him 
for increased cost of living should not be more than "0" 
168. 
If New Tax Regime is selected 
then In Schedule VIA, Professional tax u/s 16(iii) should not be more than "0" 
169. 
If New Tax Regime is selected 
then In Schedule VIA, deduction under section 80CCD(1B) should not be more than "0" 
170. 
If New Tax Regime is selected 
then In Schedule VIA, deduction under section 80EE should not be more than "0" 
171. 
If New Tax Regime is selected 
then In Schedule VIA, deduction under section 80EEA should not be more than "0" 
172. 
If New Tax Regime is selected 
then In Schedule VIA, deduction under section 80EEB should not be more than "0" 

=== PAGE 14 ===
Page 14 
 
 
173. 
If New Tax Regime is selected, then deduction u/s 80D claimed should not be more than 
"0" and details should not be provided in schedule 80D 
174. 
If New Tax Regime is selected and Income from house property is positive then Gross 
Total Income is not equal to the Total of Incomes from Salary, House Property & Other 
Sources & LTCG u/s 112A. 
  
175. 
 If New Tax Regime is selected, then deduction u/s 80GGA claimed should not be more 
than "0" and details should not be provided in schedule 80GGA 
176. 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then Exempt Allowance Sec 10(13A)-Allowance to meet 
expenditure incurred on house rent cannot be more than 1/3rd of  Salary as per section 
17(1) 
177. 
Exempt allowance u/s 10(10CC) cannot be more than the TDS claimed u/s 192 in schedule 
TDS1 
178. 
In Schedule 80D, Deduction at sl.no.1a "Self and Family" can be claimed only if dropdown 
at sl.no.1 ‘Whether you or any of your family member (excluding parents) is a senior 
citizen?’ is selected as "No" 
179. 
In Schedule 80D, Deduction at sl.no.1b "Self & Family including Senior Citizen" can be 
claimed only if dropdown at Sl.no.1 ‘Whether you or any of your family member 
(excluding parents) is a senior citizen? ‘is selected as "Yes" 
180. 
In Schedule 80D, Deduction at sl.no.2a "Parents" can be claimed only if dropdown at 
sl.no.2 ‘Whether any one of your parents is a senior citizen’ is selected as "No" 
181. 
In Schedule 80D, Deduction at sl.no.2b "Parents including Senior Citizen" can be claimed 
only if dropdown at sl.no.2 ‘Whether any one of your parents is a senior citizen’ is selected 
as "Yes" 
182. 
In Schedule 80D, deduction cannot be claimed in sl.no.1a and 1b if dropdown is selected 
as "Not claiming for Self /Family" 
183. 
In Schedule 80D, deduction cannot be claimed in sl.no.2a and 2b if dropdown is selected 
as "Not claiming for Parents" 
184. 
Any drop-down of nature of income cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt 
Income. 
 
 
185. 
Exempt Allowance u/s 10(10B) (i) and 10(10B) (ii) Should not be allowed to Central 
Government employees, state government employees, CG-Pensioners, SG- Pensioners, 
PSU-Pensioners, or Others-Pensioners 
186. 
Deduction u/s 80CCH should not exceed 46.2% of Salary u/s 17(1) 
187. 
Deduction u/s 80CCH can be claimed if Nature of employment is 'Central Government' 
and age is from 17 years to 27 years as on date of joining of armed forces.  
188. 
Exempt Allowance u/s 10(10B)-Second proviso- Compensation under scheme approved by 
the Central Government cannot exceed Rs.500,000 
189. 
If Return is filed u/s 139(5) and original return was filed u/s 139(4) 
then Old Tax Regime cannot be selected.  
190. 
Option to withdraw from New Tax Regime is not available after due date of filing of return 
as mentioned u/s 139(1) 
191. 
If New tax Regime is selected, Rebate u/s 87A is claimed by Resident Individual having 
Total income excluding LTCG of more than Rs.12,70,590. 
192. 
Rebate u/s 87A can be claimed to the extent of Rs.12500 by Resident Individual having 
Total income of Rs. 5,00,000 under old tax regime 
193. 
If 80GGC is claimed in Income Details Deduction under Chapter VIA, then same amount 
and details should be provided in Schedule 80GGC 

=== PAGE 15 ===
Page 15 
 
 
194. 
In Schedule 80GGC, 'Eligible amount of contributions' for each row shall be equal to 
"contribution in other mode" to the extent of Gross total income 
195. 
Total Contribution' should be equal to sum of "Contribution in cash" AND "Contribution in 
other mode" in table (80GGC) 
196. 
In schedule 80GGC, Sl no. D "Eligible Amount of contribution” should be equal to sum of 
individual amounts restricted to GTI 
197. 
In schedule 80GGC, Values at sl.no.A - total contribution in Cash, B-contribution in other 
mode and C-Total contribution   should be equal to sum of individual amounts entered 
198. 
Date of contribution is mandatory for contribution made under 80GGC 
199. 
Details of contribution made in other mode are required in schedule 80GGC 
200. 
 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, And In the schedule 80U value at i- 'Nature of disability' is 
selected as "self with severe disability" and the value at field ii-'Amount if deduction' is 
less or more than 125,000 subject to GTI. 
201. 
 
 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, And In the schedule 80U value at i- 'Nature of disability' is 
selected as "self with disability" and the value at field ii-'Amount of deduction' is less or 
more than 75,000 subject to GTI. 
202. 
If 80U claimed in Deduction under Chapter VIA, then same amount and details should be 
provided in Schedule 80U 
203. 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, And If drop down selected at sl no (i)-Nature of disability' 
of schedule 80DD is 'dependent person with disability' and amount is less or more  Rs. 
75000 subject to GTI. 
204. 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, And If drop down selected at sl no (i)-Nature of disability' 
of schedule 80DD is 'dependent person with severe disability' and amount is less or more  
Rs. 125000 subject to GTI. 
205. 
If 80DD is claimed in Deduction under Chapter VIA, then same amount and details should 
be provided in Schedule 80DD 
206. 
In schedule 80DD, If deduction is > 0, then details of such deduction is required 
207. 
In schedule 80U, If deduction is > 0, then details of such deduction is required 
208. 
In schedule 80U, If deduction is > 0, then details of such donation are required 
209. 
In schedule 80DD, If deduction is > 0, then details of such donation are required 
210. 
When details of Salary Income are given then 'Nature of employment' cannot be selected as 
'Not Applicable', 
211. 
Deduction u/s 80GGC can be claimed for the Contributions made between period 01.04. 
2025 to 31.03.  2026 for AY   2026-27 
212. 
Aadhaar number in Part A general information schedule should match with Aadhaar 
number as per profile  
213. 
"Exempt Allowances" in Salary under each section should be disclosed in one dropdown 
214. 
In case of new tax regime, deduction u/s 57(iia) can be availed upto 1/3rd of Family 
pension maximum of Rs. 25,000  

=== PAGE 16 ===
Page 16 
 
 
215. 
In case of New Tax Regime: 
Taxpayer being an employee can claim Standard deduction u/s 16ia only to the extent of  
Rs 75000. 
216. 
 
In case of New Tax Regime, deduction u/s 80CCD (2) should not be more than 14% of 
salary if the employer category is selected as PSU”, “Others", "Central Govt" or "State 
Govt" 
217. 
Under Exempt Income, Sl. No. iii Long term capital gains as per sec 112A should not be 
more than 1,25,000 
218. 
In Exempt Income, Sl. No. iii Long term capital gains as per sec 112A should be output of 
Sl. No. (i - ii) 
219. 
In Part A General, Filing section is selected as 139(9) and the responses for A23 in 139(9) 
is not matching with the responses of A23 question in the ITR against which defective 
response is getting submitted. 
220. 
"Details of Bank from which loan is taken" needs to be provided for claiming Interest on 
borrowed capital u/s 24(b) in schedule Interest u/s 24(b) 
221. 
Deduction u/s 80EE / 80EEA can be claimed when the limit u/s 24(b) is exhausted. 
222. 
As the deduction u/s 80EE can be claimed over and above deduction u/s 24(b), "Details of 
bank from which loan is taken" in schedule 80EE should be part of the details disclosed in 
schedule 24(b) 
223. 
As the deduction u/s 80EEA can be claimed over and above deduction u/s 24(b), "Details 
of bank from which loan is taken" in schedule 80EEA should be part of the details 
disclosed in schedule 24(b) 
224. 
Details such as Amount eligible for deduction u/s 80C, Identification Number of 
supporting document are required to provide in schedule 80C to claim deduction 
225. 
"Details of Bank from which loan is taken" need to be provided for claiming deduction u/s 
80EE in schedule 80EE 
226. 
PRAN should be provided in schedule VIA to claim deduction u/s 80CCD(1), or 
80CCD(1B) 
227. 
Deduction u/s 80EE can be claimed only if maximum loan taken does not exceed Rs. 35 
lakhs against the property 
228. 
"Details of Bank from which loan is taken" needs to be provided for claiming deduction u/s 
80EEA in schedule 80EEA 
229. 
Deduction u/s 80EEA can be claimed only on the residential house property having stamp 
duty value upto Rs.45 Lakhs 
230. 
The Date of sanction of loan under schedule 80EEA shall be between 
1.4.19 and 31.3.22 
231. 
"Details of Bank from which loan is taken" need to be provided for claiming deduction u/s 
80EEB in schedule 80EEB 
232. 
The Date of sanction of loan under schedule 80EEB shall be between 
1.4.19 and 31.3.23 
233. 
Details of Form 10BA is required to provide to claim deduction u/s 80GG 
234. 
In schedule 80D, breakup of individual rows for "amount of premium paid" shall match 
with the Health insurance premium entered by the user under "Health insurance" at sl.no.1a 
235. 
In schedule 80D, breakup of individual rows for "amount of premium paid" shall match 
with the Health insurance premium entered by the user under "Health insurance" at 
sl.no.1b 

=== PAGE 17 ===
Page 17 
 
 
236. 
In schedule 80D, breakup of individual rows for "amount of premium paid" shall match 
with the Health insurance premium entered by the user under "Health insurance" at sl.no.2a 
237. 
In schedule 80D, breakup of individual rows for "amount of premium paid" shall match 
with the Health insurance premium entered by the user under "Health insurance" at 
sl.no.2b 
238. 
Form 10IA needs to be filed separately for claiming Deduction u/s 80U and 80DD 
respectively. 
239. 
Details of specified disease is required to be provided to claim deduction u/s 80DDB 
240. 
In schedule House property, value of "interest on borrowed capital" should be same as the 
"total of interest paid u/s 24(b)" as per schedule 24(b) 
241. 
Deduction u/s 80C claimed under chapter VIA should be same as the “Total of payment 
made as per schedule 80C " 
242. 
Deduction u/s 80E in schedule VIA should match with the "Total of interest paid" as per 
schedule 80E 
243. 
Deduction u/s 80EE in schedule VIA should match with the "Total of interest paid" as per 
schedule 80EE 
244. 
Deduction u/s 80EEA in schedule VIA should match with the "Total of interest paid" as 
per schedule 80EEA 
245. 
Deduction u/s 80EEB in schedule VIA should match with the "Total of interest paid" as 
per schedule 80EEB 
246. 
In schedule 24(b) the sum of individual rows for "Interest paid during the year" (x) shall 
match with the "Total of Payments" as per the schedule 24(b) 
247. 
In schedule 80C the sum of individual rows for "Amount of payment" (ii) shall match with 
the "Total of Payments" as per the schedule 80C 
248. 
In schedule 80E the sum of individual rows for "Amount of interest paid" (x) shall match 
with the "Total of Payments" as per the schedule 80E 
249. 
In schedule 80EE the sum of individual rows for "Interest paid during the year" (x) shall 
match with the "Total of Payments" as per the schedule 80EE 
250. 
In schedule 80EEA the sum of individual rows for "Amount of interest paid" (ix) shall 
match with the "Total of Payments" as per the schedule 80EEA 
251. 
In schedule 80EEB the sum of individual rows for "Amount of interest paid" (x) shall 
match with the "Total of Payments" as per the schedule 80EEB 
252. 
The Date of sanction of loan In schedule 80EE shall be between 
1.4.16 and 31.3.17 
253. 
Interest on borrowed capital In schedule 24(b) can’t be claimed in case of Self occupied 
house property under new tax regime 
254. 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, and Deduction u/s 80D is claimed but details not provided 
in Schedule 80D 
255. 
Assessee having status as Individual and opting new tax regime have filled any of the 
schedules amongst 80C schedule, 10(13A) schedule, 80E schedule, 80EE schedule, 80EEA 
schedule or 80EEB schedule 
256. 
Details such as name of the Insurer, Policy number are required to be provided in schedule 
80D to claim deduction for health insurance at sl. No. 1a (i) 
257. 
Details such as name of the Insurer, Policy number are required to be provided in schedule 
80D to claim deduction for health insurance at sl. No. 1b (i) 

=== PAGE 18 ===
Page 18 
 
 
258. 
Details such as name of the Insurer, Policy number are required to be provided in schedule 
80D to claim deduction for health insurance at sl. No. 2a (i) 
259. 
Details such as name of the Insurer, Policy number are required to be provided in schedule 
80D to claim deduction for health insurance at sl. No. 2b (i) 
260. 
Section 192 applicable to Tax deducted on salary income is selected as the dropdown 
under schedule TDS 2, or 3 which are for details of TDS on other than salary income. 
261. 
HRA u/s 10(13A) shall not be more than Actual rent paid after deducting 10% of basic 
salary and DA 
262. 
HRA u/s 10(13A) shall not be more than 40% of basic salary and DA for those living in 
non-metro cities or, 
 shall not be more than 50% of basic salary and DA for those living in metro cities (as 
applicable) 
263. 
In schedule 10(13A) the lowest of the following amounts shall be claimed as HRA 
exemption: 
A) Actual HRA received 
B) Actual rent paid-10% of (salary+DA) 
C) 40% or 50% of (salary+DA) 
264. 
Taxpayers having salary income and exempt allowances needs to provide "Nature of 
employment" 
265. 
"Schedule 10(13A) needs to be filled for claiming exempt allowance u/s 10(13A) 
266. 
Sum of Basic salary, dearness allowance as per schedule 10(13A) and actual HRA received 
shall not be more than salary as per section 17(1) under Income details 
267. 
Exempt allowance u/s  10(10)-Death-cum-retirement gratuity received cannot be more than 
25,00,000 if nature of employment is "CG", "CG-Pensioners", "Sg" or "SG-Pensioners" 
 
268. 
Status selected is Individual and having date of formation on or after 01/04/2008 shall not 
be allowed to file return for AY 26-27 
 
269. 
Exempt Allowance u/s 10(13A) in schedule Salary should match with the "Eligible 
allowance u/s 10(13A)" as per schedule 10(13A) 
 
270. 
Exempt Allowance "Exempt income received by a judge covered under the payment of 
salaries to Supreme Court/High Court judges Act /Rules" can be claimed only by CG/SG 
employees 
 
271. 
"Type of house property" shall be mandatory if interest on borrowed capital u/s 24(b) is 
claimed. 
 
272. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80C should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
273. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80CCC should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
274. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80CCD (1) should not be more than user 
enterable amount 
275. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80CCD(1B) should not be more than user 
enterable amount 
276. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80CCD (2) should not be more than user 
enterable amount 

=== PAGE 19 ===
Page 19 
 
 
277. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80D should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
278. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80DD should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
279. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80DDB should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
280. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80E should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
281. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80EE should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
282. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80EEA should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
283. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80EEB should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
284. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80G should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
285. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80GG should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
286. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80GGA should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
287. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80GGC should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
288. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80TTA should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
289. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80TTB should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
290. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80U should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
291. 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80CCH should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
292. 
LTCG u/s 112A shall be equal to difference between GTI including LTCG and GTI 
exceluding LTCG 
293. 
In Part A General "Name of the representative, Email ID of the representative, Contact 
No. are mandatory if in Part- Verification capacity is selected as "Representative" from 
drop down 
294. 
Whether this return is being filed by a representative assessee? Flag is Y 
then details should be provided 
295. 
In case of Co-owned property, the total of assessee's share and other co-owner's share 
should be equal to 100% 
296. 
In Schedule HP, In case of co-owned property Annual value of the property owned should 
be own percentage share *Annual value. 
297. 
Assessee share of co-owned property is zero then interest on borrowed capital cannot be 
more than zero', 
298. 
In Schedule HP, Sl.no 1d -Total should be output of SL.no (1b+1c) 

=== PAGE 20 ===
Page 20 
 
 
299. 
In Schedule HP, Sl.no 1i -Total should be output of SL.no (1g+1h) 
300. 
In case of co-owned house property, Asseesee PAN & other Co-owners PAN cannot be 
same 
301. 
Exempt Allowance "Exempt income received by a judge covered under the payment of 
salaries to Supreme Court/High Court judges Act /Rules" can't be more than 0 is new tax 
regime is selected. 
302. 
If in 80CCC the sum of individual rows for "Amount" is not equal to Total of "Amounts" 
as per field 80CCC in Income details. 
 
303. 
"Sec 10(2) Member’s share from HUF" drop-down cannot be selected more than one time 
under Exempt Income. 
304. 
"Sec 10(10BB) payments made under the Bhopal Gas Leak Disaster" drop-down cannot be 
selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
305. 
"Sec 10(11A)- Sum received from an account opened under the Sukanya Samriddhi Yojan" 
drop-down cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
306. 
"Sec 10(12A) NPS partial withdrawal" drop-down cannot be selected more than one time 
under Exempt Income. 
307. 
"Sec 10(12AA) any payment from the National Pension System Trust" drop-down cannot 
be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
308. 
"Sec 10(12AB) any sum received as lump sum amount as per clause (vi) of paragraph 2 of 
the notification number FX-1/3/2024-PR" drop-down cannot be selected more than one 
time under Exempt Income. 
309. 
"Sec 10(12B) NPS lumpsum at exit/closure (portion)" drop-down cannot be selected more 
than one time under Exempt Income. 
310. 
"Sec 10(12BA) partial withdrawal made from the National Pension System" drop-down 
cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
311. 
"Sec 10(12C) Agniveer Corpus Fund income" drop-down cannot be selected more than one 
time under Exempt Income. 
312. 
"Sec 10(15) Interest on specified securities/investments" drop-down cannot be selected 
more than one time under Exempt Income. 
313. 
"Sec 10(19A) Annual value of one palace in occupation of ex-ruler" drop-down cannot be 
selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
314. 
"Sec 10(23AA) Sum received by any person on behalf of any Fund established by the 
armed force" drop-down cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
315. 
"Sec 10(23FBB)-income referred to in section 115UB, accruing or arising to, or received 
by, a unit holder of an investment fund” drop-down cannot be selected more than one time 
under Exempt Income. 
316. 
"Sec 10(23FD) Unit holder income from Business Trust (certain parts" drop-down cannot 
be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
317. 
"Sec 10(25)-Sum received by trustees on behalf of approved superannuation, gratuity, or 
pension fund" drop-down cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
318. 
"Minor child’s income—small exemption" drop-down cannot be selected more than one 
time under Exempt Income. 
319. 
"Sec 10(35) Income from specified Mutual Funds" drop-down cannot be selected more 
than one time under Exempt Income. 

=== PAGE 21 ===
Page 21 
 
 
320. 
"Sec 10(35A) distributed income referred to in section 115TA received from a 
securitization trust" drop-down cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt 
Income. 
321. 
"Sec 10(43) Reverse mortgage—payments to senior citizens" drop-down cannot be 
selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
322. 
"Sec 10(44) Income received by any person for, or on behalf of, the New Pension System 
Trusts" drop-down cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
323. 
 If New tax regime is selected, then exempt income u/s 10(32)-Minor child’s income 
should not be more than Zero 
324. 
Fees for furnishing revised return under 234-I shall be equal to Rs. 1000 if ITR is filed 
after 31/12/2026 and filing section is 139(5) and total income does not exceed 5lakh Rs. 
325. 
IFSC and "Transaction Reference number for _UPI transfer / Cheque 
number/IMPS/NEFT/RTGS reference number”, in Schedule 80G is mandatory in case of 
donation is in mode other than cash. 
326. 
IFSC and "Transaction Reference number for _UPI transfer / Cheque 
number/IMPS/NEFT/RTGS reference number”, in Schedule 80G is mandatory in case of 
donation is in mode other than cash. 
327. 
 If Old Tax Regime is selected,  
 and In "schedule 80G" if multiple entries are there under donation in cash with same PAN 
then if sum of all such cash donation does not exceeds Rs. 2000 then eligible amount of 
donation shall be allowed to the extent of Rs. 2000 or claimed whichever is lower 
328. 
Fees for furnishing revised return under 234-I shall be equal to Rs. 5000 if ITR is filed 
after 31/12/2026 and filing section is 139(5) and total income exceeds 5lakh Rs. 
329. 
Name and PAN of the political party is necessary to claim deduction u/s 80GGC 
330. 
Either cash donation or donation in other mode shall be entered under any row. 
331. 
In Part A General, Email id and contact no of the representative assessee should not match 
with Email id (primary and secondary) and contact no (primary and secondary) of 
taxpayer. 
332. 
In Schedule HP, if "Is property co-owned" is selected as Yes, then Assessee’s percentage 
of share in the Property (%) should be less than 100% 
333. 
In Schedule HP, if "Is property co-owned" is selected as Yes, then Percentage share of 
other co-owner(s) in property should be greater than 0 and less than 100% 
334. 
In case of property is not Co-owned the assessee's share should be equal to 100% 
335. 
If PRAN is entered but amount entered in 80CCD (1) and 80CCD(1B) is equal to 0 
336. 
"The amount of rent which cannot be realized" cannot be  more than Gross rent received/ 
receivable/ lettable during the year  
337. 
If Deduction u/s 80CCC is more than 0 then it shall be mandatory to add at least one row 
and provide details for "Type of identifier", "Identifier No. and "Amount" 
338. 
Secondary Address in Schedule Part A General Information is mandatory to be provided in 
the return of income 
339. 
Secondary address should not be same as Primary address if "No" is mentioned for "Is the 
secondary address same as primary address?" in Schedule Part A General Information 
 
 

=== PAGE 22 ===
Page 22 
 
 
 
1.2 Category B: 
Table 3: Category B Rules 
 
Sl.No 
Scenarios 
1 
Linking of Aadhar and PAN is required to avoid consequences of not linking PAN and 
Aadhar in eligible cases as per Circular 03/2023 
2 
Quoting of Aadhar in ITR is required as per section 139(AA)in applicable cases and also 
linking of Aadhar and PAN is required to avoid consequences of not linking PAN and Aadhar 
in eligible cases as per Circular 03/2023 
3 
TDS section code such 194B, 194BB, 194BA,194IA,194IC,194LA or 194S as is selected 
under Schedule "TDS2 Details of Tax Deducted at Source on Income Other than Salary" at 
field 2a "Section under which TDS deducted" 
 
or 
 
Assessee having income under special rate is not eligible to file ITR-1 
4 
TDS section code such 194B, 194BB, 194BA, 194IA,194IC,194LA, or 194S as is selected 
under Schedule "TDS3 Details of Tax Deducted at Source on Income Other than Salary" at 
field 2a "Section under which TDS deducted" 
 
or 
 
Assessee having income under special rate is not eligible to file ITR-1. 
5 
TDS section code such as 
194E,194LB,194LC,194LBA(a),194LBA(b),194LBA©,195,196A,196B,196C,196D or 
196D(1A) is selected under Schedule "TDS2 Details of Tax Deducted at Source on Income 
Other than Salary" at field 2a "Section under which TDS deducted" 
6 
TDS section code such as 
194E,194LB,194LC,194LBA(a),194LBA(b),194LBA©,195,196A,196B,196C,196D or 
196D(1A) is selected under Schedule "TDS3 Details of Tax Deducted at Source on Income 
Other than Salary" at field 2a "Section under which TDS deducted" 
7 
TDS section code such as 194Q, 194C or 194R is selected under Schedule "TDS2 Details of 
Tax Deducted at Source on Income Other than Salary" at field 2a "Section under which TDS 
deducted" for which ITR 1 is not applicable 
8 
TDS section code such as 194Q,194C or 194R is selected under Schedule "TDS3 Details of 
Tax Deducted at Source on Income Other than Salary" at field 2a "Section under which TDS 
deducted" for which ITR 1 is not applicable 
9 
TDS deducted value in schedule TDS 1 CANNOT BE MORE THAN value in schedule 
Salary "Total Gross salary"  
 
 
 
1.3 Category D: 
Table 4: Category D Rules 
Sl. No.  
Publishing Document 
1.  
The assessee has claimed relief u/s 89(1) without furnishing of Form 10E 
 

