=== PAGE 1 ===
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
Central Board of Direct Taxes, 
e-Filing Project 
 
ITR 4 – Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
 
Version 1.0 
15th May 2026 
 
Directorate of Income Tax (Systems) E-2,  
A.R.A. Centre, Ground Floor Jhandewalan Extension 
New Delhi – 110055 

=== PAGE 2 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
 
 
 
Document Revision List 
Document Name: ITR 4 – Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
Version Number: 1.0 
Revision Details 
 
Version No. 
Revision Date 
Revision Description 
Page Number 
1.0 
15th May 2026 
 
Initial Release 
NA 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 Page 2 

=== PAGE 3 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 3 
 
 
Contents 
Version Number: 1.0 ................................................................................................................................. 2 
1 
Purpose .................................................................................................................................................. 5 
2 
Validation Rules ................................................................................................................................. 5 
2.1 Category A: ........................................................................................................................................... 5 
2.2 Category B: ......................................................................................................................................... 23 
2.3 Category D:......................................................................................................................................... 24 
 
 

=== PAGE 4 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 4 
 
 
 
List of Tables 
Table 1: List of Category of Defect ........................................................................... 5 
Table 2: Category A Rules ....................................................................................... 5 
Table 3: Category B Rules ....................................................................................... 23 
Table 4: Category D Rule ....................................................................................... . 23 
 
 
 

=== PAGE 5 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 5 
 
 
1 
Purpose 
The Income Tax Department has provided free return preparation software in downloads page 
which are fully compliant with data quality requirements. However, there are certain 
commercially available software or websites that offer return preparation facilities as well. In 
order to ensure the data quality of ITRs prepared through such commercially available 
software, various types of validation rules are being deployed in the e-Filing portal, so that the 
data which is being uploaded are accurate and compliant to the validation rules to a large 
extent. The taxpayers are advised to review these validation rules to ensure that the software 
used by them is compliant with these requirements, to avoid rejection of return due to poor 
data quality or mistakes in the return. 
 
The software providers are strictly advised to adhere to these rules to avoid inconvenience to 
the taxpayers, who may use their software. Software providers may please note that these 
validation rules will be strictly monitored and enforced, and each rule will have to be complied 
strictly. In case of violations, the concerned return preparation utility/ software is liable to 
be blacklisted without any notice, and such blacklisting will be published on the e-filing 
website. No return using blacklisted software will be permitted to be uploaded till the time the 
software provider is able to provide details of correction in software. This may cause avoidable 
inconvenience to the taxpayers and loss of reputation to software providers for which the 
Income Tax Department will not be responsible. 
 
2 
Validation Rules 
The validation process at e-Filing/CPC end is to be carried out in ITR 4 for each defect as 
categorized below: 
 
Table 1: List of Category of Defect 
 
Category of 
defect 
Action to be Taken 
A 
Return will not be allowed to be uploaded. Error messages will be displayed. 
B 
Return data will be allowed to be uploaded but the taxpayer uploading the 
return will be informed of a possible defect present in the return u/s 139(9). 
Appropriate notices/ communications will be issued from CPC. 
D 
Return data will be allowed to be uploaded but the taxpayer uploading the 
return will be informed of the possibility of some of the deduction or claim not 
to be allowed or entertained unless the return is accompanied by the respective 
claim forms or particulars. 
 
2.1 
Category A: 
 
Table 2: Category A Rules 
 
Sl. No. 
Publishing Document 
1 
Income u/s 44AD, 44ADA, 44AE is disclosed in the Part B- Gross Total Income but 
"schedule BP" is not filled. 
2 
Business Income mentioned in Part B- Gross Total Income is not consistent with the 
amount mentioned in Schedule BP 
3 
In "Schedule BP" in E17 of Total capital and liabilities should be equal to the value 
entered in (Partners/ members own capital+Secured loans+Unsecured 
loans+Advances+Sundry creditors+Other liabilities) 

=== PAGE 6 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 6 
 
 
4 
In "Schedule BP" in E25 of Total assets should be equal to the value entered in (Fixed 
assets+Investments+Inventories +Sundry debtors+Balance with banks+Cash-in-
hand+Loans and advances+Other Assets)  
5 
Presumptive income u/s 44AD should be more than or equal to 6% of Gross Turnover or 
Gross Receipts received a/c payee cheque or a/c payee bank draft or bank electronic 
clearing system or prescribed electronic modes received before specified date  
6 
Presumptive income u/s 44AD should be more than or equal to 8% of Gross Turnover or 
Gross Receipts received in any other mode other than through a/c payee cheque or a/c 
payee bank draft or bank electronic clearing system or prescribed electronic modes 
received before specified date  
7 
Total; Presumptive income u/s 44AD should be the sum of 6% of Gross Turnover 
through Account payee check, & 8% of Gross turnover in any other mode 
8 
Income U/S 44AD is more than Gross receipts or Gross turnover 
9 
In return of income, the taxpayer has filed ITR-4 but the gross receipt/income U/S 44AD 
is more than Rs 3 crore 
10 
The provisions of 44AD are not applicable for General commission agents and persons 
carrying on professions as referred to in section 44AA (1). 
11 
In schedule BP if income is declared u/s 44AD then it is mandatory to select "Business 
code" u/s 44AD. 
12 
In schedule BP if "business code" u/s 44AD is selected then it is mandatory to declare 
income u/s 44AD. 
13 
Income U/S 44ADA is more than corresponding gross receipts. 
14 
Presumptive Income u/s 44ADA is less than 50% of Gross Turnover or Gross Receipts. 
15 
The provisions of 44ADA are not applicable for persons carrying on business 
16 
In schedule BP if income is declared u/s 44ADA then it is mandatory to select "Business 
code" u/s 44ADA. 
17 
In schedule BP if "business code" u/s 44ADA is selected then it is mandatory to declare 
income u/s 44ADA. 
18 
Total of chapter VI-A deductions is not consistent with the breakup of individual 
deductions. 
19 
Deductions claimed under Chapter VI-A are greater than “Gross Total Income” 
20 
Assessee being Firm and claiming deduction u/s 80C, 80CCC & 80CCD (1)  
21 
If Old tax regime is selected   then Sum of deductions claimed u/s 80C, 80CCC & 
80CCD (1) should not be more than 1,50,000.  
22 
If Old tax regime is selected and employer category is CG - Pensioners SG - Pensioners, 
PSU - Pensioners, others - Pensioners, or Not Applicable, then Deduction u/s 80CCD (1) 
should not be more than 20% of Gross total Income 
23 
Assessee not being an individual has claimed deduction u/s 80CCD (1) which is not 
allowable. 
24 
Taxpayer other than individual and claiming deduction u/s 80CCD(1B) 
25 
Deduction u/s 80CCD (2) should not be more than 10% of salary by an employer other 
than Central Government or "State Govt" in case of old tax regime. 
26 
Deduction u/s 80CCD (2) is claimed by HUF or Firm (other than LLP) 
27 
Assessee being Firm (other than LLP) and claiming deduction u/s 80D 
28 
Firm has claimed deduction u/s 80DD' 
29 
If Old tax regime is selected and Assessee is claiming deduction under section 80DD 
then eligible category description shall be provided 
30 
 If Old tax regime is selected and Assessee is claiming deduction under section 80DDB 
then eligible category description shall be provided 
31 
Assessee being Firm and claiming deduction u/s 80DDB 

=== PAGE 7 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 7 
 
 
32 
Deduction u/s 80EE is claimed by HUF or Firm (other than LLP) 
33 
Deduction u/s 80EE is claimed by HUF or Firm (other than LLP) 
34 
If Old Tax Regime is selected and Deduction u/is 80G claimed but however details are 
not provided in Schedule 80G 
35 
If Old Tax Regime is selected and In Schedule 80G, Amount of deduction computed is 
more than the eligible amount 
36 
If Old Tax Regime is selected and In Schedule VIA, deduction claimed u/s 80G is shall 
not be more than the eligible amount of donation mentioned in Schedule 80G 
37 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, In Schedule Income Details, the maximum limit 
allowable under section 80GG is: 
 Rs.60,000/- or  
25% of total income excluding LTCG before allowing deduction of this expenditure 
38 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, Deduction u/s 80TTA should be restricted to interest 
income from a Savings Account under Income from other sources. 
39 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, Deduction under section 80TTA cannot be claimed by 
Senior Citizen (date of birth is on or Before 01.04.1966) 
40 
If Old Tax Regime is selected and Assessee not being a senior citizen cannot claim 
deduction under section 80TTB (date of birth is on or after 02.04.1966) 
41 
If Old Tax Regime is selected and Assessee being a senior citizen claiming deduction u/s 
80TTB should be restricted to interest income (Savings & Deposits) from other sources 
or maximum limit of Rs. 50,000, whichever is lower. 
42 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then the fixed amount of Rs. 75,000 can be claimed u/s 
80U for category "Self with disability, 
43 
Assessee being HUF/Firm and claiming deduction under section 80U. 
44 
If Old Tax Regime is selected and the assessee is claiming deduction under section 80U, 
however, the description has not been provided for eligible category. 
45 
In Part A General "Name of the representative, are mandatory if in Part- Verification 
capacity is selected as "Representative" from drop down 
46 
Total income should be the difference between "Gross total income" and "Total 
deductions" 
Note: Gross total income shall include LTCG u/s 112A 
47 
In case of old tax regime deduction u/s 80CCD (2) should not be more than 14% of 
salary if the employer category is selected as Central Government or State Govt 
48 
The name as entered by you in the return does not match with the name as per the PAN 
date base 
49 
If Old Tax Regime is selected   and Gross Total Income is not equal to the Total of 
Incomes from Business & profession, Salary, House Property & Other Sources & Long-
term capital gains as per sec 112A. 
50 
Assessee being HUF or FIRM and claiming rebate u/s 87A  
51 
Rebate u/s 87A is claimed by Resident Individual having Total income (including LTCG 
u/s 112A) of more than Rs. 5,00,000 under old tax regime 
52 
The amount of "Tax after Rebate " should be equal to "Tax payable on total income" 
Minus "Rebate u/s 87A" 
53 
Total Tax and Health and Education cess must be equal to the sum of "Tax payable after 
Rebate" and Health and Education Cess 
54 
Total Tax, Fee, and Interest" must be equal to the sum of "Balance Tax After Relief" and 
"Interest u/s 234A, 234B, 234C, Fees u/s 234-I & Fee u/s 234F" 
55 
In Schedule Part B- Gross Total Income, Sl.no B3iii. Annual Value should be output of 
SL.no B3i-B3ii 

=== PAGE 8 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 8 
 
 
56 
In "Schedule Income Details" Balance Tax after relief should be equal to the sum of 
Total Tax &Cess -Relief u/s 89(1). 
57 
Standard deduction allowed on House property should be equal to 30% of Annual value. 
58 
Gross rent received/ receivable/ lettable value during the year is zero or null and assessee 
is claiming municipal tax 
59 
Taxpayers have selected type of property as let-out or deemed let out and Gross rent 
received/ receivable/ lettable value during the year is zero or null 
60 
In Schedule Gross total Income, Sl.no B3k .Income chargeable under the head ‘House 
Property’(f-i-j) is not equal to sum of B3(f-i-j) or The sum of Individual values under the 
head of House Property cannot be different from the "Income chargeable under the head 
House Property".   
61 
In "Schedule Income Details" Tax paid to local authorities shall not be allowed for Type 
of House Property as "Self-Occupied" 
62 
In "Schedule Income Details" Income from other sources should be equal to amount 
entered in individual col. of income from other sources 
63 
Gross salary should be total of salary as per section 17(1) and value of perquisites as per 
section 17(2) and profits in lieu of salary as per section 17(3)  
64 
In the Schedule "Gross total Income", 'Net Salary' should be the difference between 
'Gross salary' and ‘Allowances to the extent exempt u/s 10') 
65 
In income details, B2(iv) Deductions u/s 16 should be sum of B2[iva+ivb+ivc] 
66 
In income details, Sl.no B2v Income chargeable under Salaries should be B2(iii)-B2(iv) 
67 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, For Central, State Govt, & PSU employees the 
Entertainment allowance u/s 16(ii) will be allowed to the extent of Rs 5000 or 1/5th of 
Basic salary whichever is lower 
68 
No Entertainment allowance u/s 16(ii) will be allowed to employees other than Central, 
State Government, and PSU 
69 
Total of all allowances to the extent exempt u/s 10 cannot be more than the sum of 
B2(i)(a) +B2(i)(b) +B2(i)(c) 
70 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, Sec 10(5)-Leave Travel concession/assistance received 
cannot be more than Salary as per section 17(1). 
71 
Exempt allowance Sec 10(6)-Remuneration received as an official, by whatever name 
called, of an embassy, high commission etc." cannot be more than Gross Salary 
72 
Exempt allowance u/s 10(7)-Allowances or perquisites paid or allowed as such outside 
India by the Government to a citizen of India for rendering service outside India cannot 
be more than Gross salary 
73 
Exempt allowance u/s 10(10)-Death-cum-retirement gratuity received cannot be more 
than 20,00,000 if nature of employment is Public Sector Undertaking, PSU - Pensioners, 
others - Pensioners, Others 
74 
Sec 10(10A)-Commuted value of pension received cannot be more than Salary as per 
section 17(1) 
75 
Sec 10(10AA)-Earned leave encashment cannot be more than Salary as per section 17(1) 
76 
Exempt Allowance u/s 10(10C)-Amount received/receivable on voluntary retirement or 
termination of service cannot exceed Rs. 5,00,000 
77 
In exempt allowances only Sec 10(10B) (i) OR Sec 10(10B) (ii) OR Sec 10(10C) can be 
selected. 
78 
Exempt Allowance u/s 10(10CC)-Tax paid by employer on non-monetary perquisite 
cannot be more than Value of perquisites as per section 17(2) 
79 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, Exempt Allowance Sec 10(13A)-Allowance to meet 
expenditure incurred on house rent cannot be more than 1/3rd 33.33% 50% of Salary as 
per section 17(1) 

=== PAGE 9 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 9 
 
 
80 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, Sec 10(14)(i) Prescribed Allowances or benefits (not in a 
nature of perquisite) specifically granted to meet expenses wholly, necessarily and 
exclusively and to the extent actually incurred, in performance of duties of office or 
employment cannot be more than Salary as per section 17(1) 
81 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, Sec 10(14)(ii) Prescribed Allowances or benefits granted 
to meet personal expenses in performance of duties of office or employment or to 
compensate him for increased cost of living cannot be more than Salary as per section 
17(1) 
82 
"Sec 10(10BC)-Any amount from the Central/State Govt./local authority by way of 
compensation on account of any disaster" drop-down cannot be selected more than one 
time under Exempt Income. 
83 
"Sec 10(10D)- Any sum received under a life insurance policy, including the sum 
allocated by way of bonus on such policy except sum as mentioned in sub-clause (a) to 
(d) of Sec.10(10D)" drop-down cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt 
Income. 
84 
"Sec 10(11)-Statutory Provident Fund received" drop-down cannot be selected more than 
one time under Exempt Income. 
85 
"Sec 10(12)-Recognized Provident Fund received" drop-down cannot be selected more 
than one time under Exempt Income. 
86 
"Sec 10(13)-Approved superannuation fund received" drop-down cannot be selected 
more than one time under Exempt Income. 
87 
"Sec 10(16)-Scholarships granted to meet the cost of education" drop-down cannot be 
selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
88 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, "Sec 10(17)-Allowance MP/MLA/MLC" drop-down 
cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt Allowances under salary schedule. 
89 
"Sec 10(17A)-Award instituted by Government" drop-down cannot be selected more 
than one time under Exempt Income. 
90 
"Sec 10(18)-Pension received by winner of “Param Vir Chakra" or "Maha Vir Chakra" 
or "Vir Chakra" or such other gallantry award", drop-down cannot be selected more than 
one time under Exempt Income. 
91 
"Defense Medical Disability Pension" drop-down cannot be selected more than one time 
under Exempt Income. 
92 
"Sec 10(19)-Armed Forces Family pension in case of death during operational duty" 
drop-down cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
93 
"Sec 10(26)-Any income as referred to in section 10(26)" drop-down cannot be selected 
more than one time under Exempt Income. 
94 
"Sec 10(26AAA)-Any income as referred to in section 10(26AAA)" drop-down cannot 
be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
95 
In "Schedule Income Details" Deduction u/s 57(iia) shall be allowed only if "Family 
pension" is selected from other sources dropdown. 
96 
In case of old tax regime in “Schedule Income Details" Deduction u/s 57(iia) cannot be 
more than 1/3rd of Family pension or Rs. 15,000 whichever is lower. 
97 
Presumptive income u/s 44AE should be Presumptive Income from Goods Carriage as 
reduced by Salary and interest paid to partners in respect of taxpayers who have selected 
status as "Firm (other than LLP)" 
98 
In Sch 80G Donee PAN is same as "Assessee PAN" or "PAN at Verification" 
99 
In Schedule 80G in table (A) "Donations entitled for 100% deduction without qualifying 
limit" donation in cash or donation in other mode is to be entered mandatory. 
100 
In Schedule 80G in table (B) "Donations entitled for 50% deduction without qualifying 
limit" donation in cash or donation in other mode is to be entered mandatory. 

=== PAGE 10 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 10 
 
 
101 
In Schedule 80G in table (c) “Donations entitled for 100% deduction Subject to 
Qualifying Limit" Donation in cash or Donation in other mode is to be entered 
mandatory. 
102 
In Schedule 80G in table (D) “Donations entitled for 50% deduction Subject to 
Qualifying Limit" Donation in cash or Donation in other mode is to be entered 
mandatory. 
103 
In Schedule 80G in table (E) Donations should be equal to the sum of (Donations entitled 
for 100% deduction without qualifying limit +Donations entitled for 50% deduction 
without qualifying limit+Donations entitled for 100% deduction subject to qualifying 
limit+Donations entitled for 50% deduction subject to qualifying limit) 
104 
"Total Donation" should be equal to sum of "Donation in cash" AND "Donation in other 
mode" in table (80G) (A)"Donations entitled for 100% deduction without qualifying 
limit" 
105 
Total Donation' should be equal to sum of "Donation in cash" AND "Donation in other 
mode" in table (80G) (B)"Donations entitled for 50% deduction without qualifying limit" 
106 
Total Donation' should be equal to sum of "Donation in cash" AND "Donation in other 
mode" in table (80G) (C)"Donations entitled for 100% deduction subject to qualifying 
limit" 
107 
Total Donation' should be equal to sum of "Donation in cash" AND "Donation in other 
mode" in table (80G) (D)"Donations entitled for 50% deduction subject to qualifying 
limit"  
108 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, and in "schedule 80G" if multiple entries are there under 
donation in cash with same PAN, then, if sum of all such cash donation exceeds Rs. 2000 
then eligible amount of donation shall not be more than 0 
or in case of individual entry is more than Rs. 2000 in cash then also eligible amount of 
donation shall not be more than 0 
109 
In schedule 80G, if donation is made, same PAN of Donee cannot appear more than once 
except the PAN 'AAAAR1077P can be repeated in different blocks' 
Note: For table D (50% without qualifying limit), above rule will not be applicable if 
ARN number is unique. Further if ARN is not entered then this note will not be 
applicable 
110 
In Schedule IT total of Col 4 Tax Paid should be equal to sum of individual values 
111 
In Schedule TCS, “The Amount of TCS claimed this year” is more than “Tax collected” 
112 
In Schedule TCS total of col 5 TCS credit out of (4) being claimed this year should be 
equal to sum of individual values 
113 
In Schedule TDS2 (i) & (ii) (Other than salary), “The Amount of TDS claimed this year” 
is more than “Tax deducted”. 
114 
In Schedule TDS (2), year of tax deduction cannot be '0' / 'null ' if there is a claim of 
brought forward TDS  
115 
In Schedule TDS2(i) & TDS2(ii), Unclaimed TDS brought forward & details of TDS of 
current FY should be provided in different rows in Sch TDS 2  
116 
In schedule TDS-2(ii), claim of TDS in S. No 6 cannot be more than income disclosed in 
SR.NO 7 
117 
In schedule TDS-2(i), claim of TDS in SR.NO 6 cannot be more than income disclosed 
in SR.NO 7 
118 
In Schedule TDS1 total of col 4 'Total Tax deducted" should be equal to sum of 
individual values of col 4 
119 
In Schedule TDS2 total of col 6 'TDS Credit out of (5) being claimed this year' should be 
equal to sum of individual values of col 6 
120 
In Schedule TDS3 total of col 6' 'TDS Credit out of (5) claimed this year' should be equal 
to sum of individual values of col 6 

=== PAGE 11 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 11 
 
 
121 
In schedule "Tax Details" in TDS2(i), TDS is claimed in column 6 then Corresponding 
Receipt /Withdrawals offered - "Gross Amount 
(Col 7)" and "Head of Income 
(Col 8)" is to be mandatorily filled. 
122 
In schedule "Tax Details" in TDS2(ii), TDS is claimed in column 6 then Corresponding 
Income offered - "Gross Amount (Col 7)" and "Head of Income (Col 8)" is to be 
mandatorily filled. 
123 
IFSC under “Bank Details,” Schedule 80G and in schedule 80GGC should match with 
the RBI database / GIFT IFSC codes. 
124 
Tax computation has been disclosed but Gross Total Income is zero. 
125 
"Income details" and "Tax computation" have not been disclosed but details regarding 
“Taxes Paid” have been disclosed. 
126 
TDS, TCS or Tax paid claimed in “Tax paid and Verification schedule” is inconsistent 
with details of tax amount paid provided in Schedule IT, Schedule TDS1, Schedule 
TDS2 and Schedule TCS.  
127 
The sum of the amounts claimed at TDS, TCS, Advance Tax and Self-Assessment Tax is 
not equal to the amount claimed at “Total Taxes Paid.” 
128 
Amount of Refund claimed is inconsistent with the difference of “Total Taxes Paid” and 
“Total Tax, Fee & Interest” 
129 
Amount of Tax payable is inconsistent with the difference of “Total Tax, Fee and 
Interest” and “Total Taxes Paid.” 
130 
Agriculture Income shown as exempt cannot be more than Rs 5,000/- and cannot be 
selected more than once. 
131 
In "Schedule Taxes Paid and Verification" Total TDS Claimed should be equal to the 
sum of total TDS claimed in TDS 1, 2(i) & 2(ii) 
132 
In "Schedule Taxes Paid and Verification" Total TCS Claimed should be equal to the 
sum of total TCS claimed in TCS schedule 
133 
In "Schedule Taxes Paid and Verification" Total Advance Tax paid should be equal to 
the sum of total Tax Paid in schedule IT where date of deposit is in the PY for which ITR 
is being filed. 
134 
In "Schedule Taxes Paid and Verification" Total Self-Assessment Tax Paid should be 
equal to the sum of total Tax Paid in schedule IT where date of deposit is after 31st Mar 
of the PY for which ITR is being filed. 
135 
The value at field "E5" is greater than zero but the Schedule 44AE is not filed. 
136 
Presumptive Income from Goods Carriage under section 44AE is not equal to the amount 
mentioned in "Presumptive income u/s 44AE" 
137 
In schedule BP if income is declared u/s 44AE then it is mandatory to select "Business 
code" u/s 44AE. 
138 
In schedule BP if "business code" u/s 44AE is selected then it is mandatory to declare 
income u/s 44AE. 
139 
Gross receipts /turnover are mentioned in schedule BP but Financial Particulars such as 
Sundry creditors, Inventories, Sundry debtors, cash in hand is not filled  
140 
As per rule 12 (1) (ca), a person deriving income under the head “profits or gains from 
business /profession” and such income computed in accordance with special provisions 
of section 44AD or 44AE or 44ADA, is required to furnished return in ITR-4. The 
Return of Income is filed using ITR 4, however, income from business or profession 
under section 44AD or 44AE or 44ADA is not disclosed. 
141 
Taxpayer has filed ITR 4 and mentioned Number of months for which goods carriage 
was owned/ leased/hired by assessee by assessee more than 12 months AND / OR total 
period of holding more than 120 months 

=== PAGE 12 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 12 
 
 
142 
Credit for TDS has been claimed in return, but the corresponding receipts have been 
omitted to be offered for taxation. 
143 
Taxpayer being an employee can claim Standard deduction u/s 16ia only to the extent of 
Rs 50000 in case of old tax regime 
144 
“The presumptive income offered u/s 44AE per vehicle is less than Rs.1000 per MT per 
month (where the tonnage capacity exceeds 12 MT) or Rs. 7500 per month (where the 
tonnage capacity does not exceed 12 MT)". 
145 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, Deduction u/s 80CCD1(B) is limited to 50000 
146 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then fixed amount that can be claimed for category 
"Dependent with disability" u/s 80DD should be equal to its Rs. 75,000 
147 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then fixed amount is Rs. 125,000 can be claimed for 
category "Dependent with severe disability" u/s 80DD should be equal to Rs. 125,000 
148 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, and In Schedule Part BTI, Assessee has claimed 
deduction u/s 80DDB for self and dependent more than the maximum limit of 
Rs.40,000/- 
149 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, and In Schedule Part BTI, Assessee has claimed 
deduction u/s 80DDB for Category "senior citizen self and dependent "more than the 
maximum limit of Rs.100,000/- 
150 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, and In Schedule Part BTI, assessee has claimed deduction 
u/s 80EE is more than the maximum limit of Rs.50,000  
151 
House rent allowance (HRA u/s.10(13A)) is claimed, hence deduction u/s.80GG above 
Rs 55,000 not allowed 
152 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, the maximum deduction allowed under section 80TTA is 
Rs.10,000/-. 
153 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, the maximum deduction allowed under section 80TTB is 
Rs.50,000/-. 
154 
If Old Tax Regime is selected and In Schedule HP, if "Type of House Property" is 
selected as "Self-Occupied”, then assessee cannot claim interest on borrowed capital 
more than Rs 2,00,000, 
155 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then in case employer category is other than CG - 
Pensioners SG - Pensioners, PSU - Pensioners, others - Pensioners or "not applicable" 
then the Maximum amount that can be claimed for u/s 80CCD (1) is 10% of Salary  
156 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, and Assessee is claiming deduction u/s 80EEA more than 
the maximum limit of Rs 150000/- 
157 
If Old Tax Regime is selected and Deductions claimed under section 80EEA is greater 
than “Zero" and Deductions claimed under section 80EE is greater than “Zero" 
158 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, and Assessee claiming deduction u/s 80EEB more than 
the maximum limit of Rs 150000/- 
159 
Exempt Allowance u/s 10(10B)-First Proviso- Compensation limit notified by CG in the 
Official Gazette cannot exceed Rs.500,000 
160 
In Income details, allowance to extent exempt u/s 10 should be equal to sum of 
individual values entered. 
161 
Deduction u/s 80CCD (2) cannot be claimed by the taxpayer who has selected employer 
category as CG - Pensioners SG - Pensioners, PSU - Pensioners, others - Pensioners or 
"not applicable" 
162 
Relief u/s 89 cannot be claimed by taxpayer if details of salary and family pension are 
"zero"/ "blank" 
163 
Deduction u/s 80EEA is claimed by HUF or Firm (other than LLP) 
164 
Deduction u/s 80EEB is claimed by HUF or Firm (other than LLP) 
165 
Assessee is "HUF" or Firm (other than LLP) and amount in schedule TDS 1 is more than 
zero 

=== PAGE 13 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 13 
 
 
166 
Assessee is "HUF" or Firm (other than LLP) and amount in details of salary is more than 
zero 
167 
If the original return is filed under section 142(1) then taxpayer cannot file revised return 
168 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then In Schedule 80D, Deduction at Sl. No. 1a "Self and 
Family" will be allowed to the extent of Rs. 25000 
169 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then In Schedule 80D, Deduction at Sl. No. 1a should be 
equal to sum of Sl. No (i+ii) 
Note: This validation is to be checked if value of (i+ii) of Sl. No. 1a is less than 
Rs.25000 
170 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then In Schedule 80D, the amount of preventive health 
checkup of all the fields combined should not exceed Rs. 5000 
171 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then In Schedule 80D, Deduction at Sl. No. 1b Self and 
Family (Senior Citizen) will be allowed to the extent of Rs.50000 
172 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then In Schedule 80D, Deduction at Sl. No. 1b should be 
equal to sum of Sl. No (i+ii+iii) 
Note: This validation to be checked if value of (i+ii+iii) of Sl. No. 1b is less than 
Rs.50000 
173 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, In Schedule 80D, Deduction at Sl. No. 2a Parents will be 
allowed to the extent of Rs. 25000 
174 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then In Schedule 80D, Deduction at Sl. No. 2a should be 
equal to sum of Sl. No (i+ii) Note: This validation is to be checked if value of (i+ii) of Sl. 
No. 2a is less than RS.25000 
175 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, In Schedule 80D, Deduction at Sl. No. 2b Parents (Senior 
Citizen) will be allowed to the extent of Rs.50000 
176 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then In Schedule 80D, Deduction at Sl. No. 2b should be 
equal to sum of Sl. No (i+ii+iii) Note: This validation is to be checked if value of 
(i+ii+iii) of Sl. No. 2b is less than Rs.50000 
177 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, In Schedule 80D, Sl. No. 3 Eligible amount of deduction 
will be allowed to the extent of Rs.100000 
178 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, then In Schedule 80D, Eligible amount of deduction at Sl. 
No. 3 should be equal to sum of Sl. No (1a+1b+2a+2b) subject to GTI Note: This 
validation to be checked, if value of Sl. No. (1a+1b+2a+2b) is less than or equal to 
Rs.100000 
179 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, and Deduction u/s 80D is claimed but details not provided 
in Schedule 80D 
180 
Income from Family Pension cannot be claimed by "Firm (Other than LLP)" and "HUF" 
181 
If exempt allowance is claimed u/s. 10(10AA) above Rs. 25 Lakh for employer category 
other "Central and state government, CG-Pensioners or SG-Pensioner" 
182 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, The fixed amount of Rs. 125,000 can be claimed u/s 80U 
for category "Self-severe with disability" 
183 
  If New Tax regime is selected, then Part C – Deductions and Taxable Total Income, all 
the deductions should not be more than "0" other than 80CCD (2) and 80CCH  
184 
  If New Tax regime is selected, Then Exempt allowances under 
Sec 10(5)-Leave Travel concession/assistance 
Sec 10(13A)-Allowance to meet expenditure incurred on house rent 
Sec 10(14)(i)- Prescribed Allowances or benefits (not in a nature of perquisite) 
specifically granted to meet expenses wholly, necessarily and exclusively and to the 
extent actually incurred, in performance of duties of office or employment 
Sec 10(14)(ii) -Prescribed Allowances or benefits granted to meet personal expenses in 
performance of duties of office or employment or to compensate him for increased cost 
of living 
should not be more than "0" 

=== PAGE 14 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 14 
 
 
185 
In income details, total of Dividend income should be equal to sum of “Quarterly 
breakup of Dividend Income"  
186 
Exempt allowance under Section 10(14)(ii) - “Transport allowance granted to certain 
physically handicapped assessee" should not exceed Rs 38,400 
187 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, Then Exempt allowances under  
Section 10(14)(i) - Allowances referred in sub-clauses (a) to (c) of sub-rule (1) in Rule 
2BB 
Section 10(14)(ii) - Transport allowance granted to certain physically handicapped 
assessee 
should not be more than "0" 
188 
Once a proceeding is initiated u/s148, the original return filed u/s 139 cannot be revised 
189 
If New Tax Regime is selected, then Sum of deductions claimed u/s 80C, 80CCC & 
80CCD (1) should not be more than zero. 
190 
If New Tax Regime is selected, then deduction u/s 80G cannot be claimed and details 
should not be provided in schedule 80G 
191 
If New Tax Regime is selected, then deduction u/s 80GG cannot be claimed and details 
should not be provided in schedule 80GG 
192 
If New Tax Regime is selected, then deduction u/s 80TTA should not be more than zero. 
193 
If New Tax Regime is selected, then deduction u/s 80TTB should not be more than zero. 
194 
If New Tax Regime is selected, then deduction u/s 80U should not be more than zero. 
195 
If New Tax Regime is selected, then Professional tax u/s 16(iii) should not be more than 
zero. 
196 
If new tax regime is selected, then Gross Total Income should be equal to the Total of 
Incomes from Business & profession, Salary, House Property, & Other Sources & LTCG 
u/s 112A. 
197 
If new tax regime is selected and Income from one House Property is negative, then 
Gross Total Income should be equal to the Total of Incomes from Business & profession, 
Salary & Other Sources, LTCG u/s 112A. 
198 
If New tax regime is selected, then Sec 10(5)-Leave Travel concession/assistance 
received should not be more than zero. 
199 
If New tax regime is selected, then Sec 10(13A)-Allowance to meet expenditure incurred 
on house rent should not be more than zero. 
200 
If New tax regime is selected, then Sec 10(14)(i) Prescribed Allowances or benefits (not 
in a nature of perquisite) specifically granted to meet expenses, necessarily and 
exclusively and to the extent actually incurred, in performance of duties of office or 
employment should not be more than zero. 
201 
If New tax regime is selected, then Sec 10(14)(ii) Prescribed Allowances or benefits 
granted to meet personal expenses in performance of duties of office or employment or 
to compensate him for increased cost of living should not be more than zero. 
202 
If New tax regime is selected, then exempt allowance u/s 10(17)-Allowance 
MP/MLA/MLC should not be more than zero 
203 
If New tax regime is selected, then deduction u/s 80CCD(1B) should not be more than 
zero. 
204 
If New tax regime is selected, then deduction u/s 80DD should not be more than zero. 
205 
If New tax regime is selected, then deduction u/s 80DDB should not be more than zero. 
206 
If New tax regime is selected, then deduction u/s 80EE should not be more than zero. 
207 
If New tax regime is selected, and "Type of House Property" is selected as "Self-
Occupied" then interest on borrowed capital should not be more than zero. 
208 
If New tax regime is selected, then deduction u/s 80CCD (1) should not be more than 
zero. 
209 
If New tax regime is selected, then deduction u/s 80EEA should not be more than zero. 

=== PAGE 15 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 15 
 
 
210 
If New tax regime is selected, then deduction u/s 80EEB should not be more than zero. 
211 
If New tax regime is selected, then deduction u/s 80D cannot be claimed and details 
should not be provided in schedule 80D 
212 
HUF is not eligible to claim presumptive income u/s 44ADA. 
213 
In Schedule BP, Registration No. of goods carriage should not be repeated in section 
44AE. 
214 
Exempt allowance u/s 10(10B)-First proviso, 10(10B)-Second Proviso and 10(10C) 
cannot be claimed simultaneously 
215 
Exempt allowance u/s 10(10CC) cannot be more than the TDS claimed u/s 192 in 
schedule TDS1 
216 
In Schedule 80D, Deduction at Sl.no.1a "Self and Family" can be claimed only if 
dropdown at sl.no.1 is selected as "No" 
217 
In Schedule 80D, Deduction at sl.no.1b "Self & Family including Senior Citizen" can be 
claimed only if dropdown at sl.no.1 is selected as "Yes" 
218 
In Schedule 80D, Deduction at sl.no.2a "Parents" can be claimed only if dropdown at 
sl.no.2 is selected as "No" 
219 
In Schedule 80D, Deduction at sl.no.2b "Parents including Senior Citizen" can be 
claimed only if dropdown at sl.no.2 is selected as "Yes" 
220 
In Schedule 80D, deduction cannot be claimed in sl.no.1a and 1b if dropdown is selected 
as "Not claiming for Self /Family" 
221 
In Schedule 80D, deduction cannot be claimed in sl.no.2a and 2b if dropdown is selected 
as "Not claiming for Parents" 
222 
Any drop-down of nature of income cannot be selected more than one time under 
Exempt Income. 
223 
Exempt Allowance u/s 10(10B) (i) and 10(10B) (ii) Should not be allowed to Central 
Government employees, state government employees, CG-Pensioners, SG- Pensioners, 
PSU-Pensioners, and Others-Pensioners 
224 
Deduction u/s 80CCH should not exceed 46.2% of Salary u/s 17(1) to the extent of 
Rs.2,88,000 
225 
Deduction u/s 80CCH can be claimed if Nature of employment is 'Central Government' 
and age is from 17 years to 27 years as on date of joining of armed forces 
226 
Exempt Allowance u/s 10(10B)-Second proviso- Compensation under scheme approved 
by the Central Government cannot exceed Rs.500,000 
227 
Assessee with total income excluding LTCG exceeding Rs.1200000 subject to marginal 
rebate (if any) cannot claim Rebate u/s 87A. Please refer to section 87A of Income tax 
act, 1961. 
228 
Details of Form 10IEA are mandatory if "Yes" is selected in field "Have you 
filed form 10IEA within due date for any earlier assessment year for choosing old tax 
regime? " 
229 
Rebate u/s 87A can be claimed to the extent of Rs.12500 by Resident Individual having 
Total income of Rs. 5,00,000 under old tax regime 
230 
Firm is eligible to claim VIA deductions under section 80G and 80GGC  
231 
HUF is eligible to claim VIA deductions under section 80G, 80GGC, 80D, 80C, 80DD, 
80DDB, 80TTA 
232 
HUF is not eligible for claiming deduction at sl.no.2 of Schedule 80D 
233 
"Exempt Allowances" in Salary under each section should be disclosed in one dropdown 
234 
Due date of Filing u/s 139(1) 31st August of respective Assessment year unless it is 
extended. 
235 
Tax regimes are not applicable for Firm and by default "not applicable" shall be selected 
and all other fields of A23 should be greyed off for them. 

=== PAGE 16 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 16 
 
 
236 
Deduction u/s 80D is not applicable for Firm 
237 
If Gross Receipts u/s 44AD are more than Rs.2 Crore and cash receipts are more than 5% 
of total receipts, it is mandatory to have a tax audit under 44AB. So, ITR 3/ ITR 5 are 
applicable 
238 
If Gross Receipts u/s 44ADA are more than Rs.5000000 and cash receipts are more than 
5% of total receipts, it is mandatory to have a tax audit under 44AB. So, ITR 3/ ITR 5 are 
applicable 
239 
If Gross Receipts u/s 44ADA at sl.no. E3 should match with sum of E3a+E3b+E3c 
240 
If Gross Receipts u/s 44AD at sl.no. E1 should match with sum of E1a+E1b+E1c 
241 
If 80GGC is claimed in Income Details Deduction under Chapter VIA, then same 
amount and details should be provided in Schedule 80GGC 
242 
In Schedule 80GGC, 'Eligible amount of Donations' for each row shall be equal to 
"Donation in other mode" to the extent of Gross total income 
243 
Total Donation' should be equal to sum of "Donation in cash" AND "Donation in other 
mode" in table (80GGC) 
244 
In schedule 80GGC, Sl no. D "Eligible Amount of donation” should be equal to sum of 
individual amounts restricted to GTI 
245 
In schedule 80GGC, Values at sl.no. A - total Donation in Cash, B-Donation in other 
mode and C-Total Donation   should be equal to sum of individual amounts entered 
246 
Date of donation is mandatory for donation made under 80GGC 
247 
Details of Donation made in other mode are required in schedule 80GGC 
248 
In schedule VIA, value at field "Section 80DD" both user value and system value should 
be equal to value at slno. ii in schedule 80DD 
249 
In schedule VIA, value at field "Section 80U" both user value and system value should 
be equal to value at slno. ii in schedule 80U 
250 
In schedule 80DD, if deduction is > 0, then details of such donation are required 
251 
In schedule 80U, if deduction is > 0, then details of such donation are required 
252 
In schedule 80DD, if deduction is > 0, then details of Form 10IA of such donation are 
required 
253 
In schedule 80U, if deduction is > 0, then details of Form 10IA of such donation are 
required 
254 
HUF can claim deductions u/s 80DD for dependent being "Member of HUF" 
255 
Taxpayers having salary income need to provide "Nature of employment" 
256 
Deduction u/s 80GGC can be claimed for the Contributions made between period 
01.04.2025 to 31.03.2026 for AY 2026-27 
257 
Aadhaar number in Part A general information schedule should match with Aadhaar 
number as per profile  
258 
Aadhaar number in Part A general information schedule should match with Aadhaar 
number as per profile  
259 
Assessee should enter valid Mobile Number 
260 
It is mandatory to select an Option for 115BAC question at sl.no. A23 
Note: Applicable in case of Individual and HUF 
261 
In case of new tax regime, deduction u/s 57(iia) can be availed up to 1/3rd of Family 
pension maximum of Rs. 25,000 
262 
In case of New Tax Regime: 
Taxpayer being an employee can claim Standard deduction u/s 16ia only to the extent of 
Rs 75000. 
263 
In case of new tax regime deduction u/s 80CCD (2) should not be more than 14% of 
salary if the employer category is selected as PSU”, “Others", "Central Govt" or "State 
Govt" 

=== PAGE 17 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 17 
 
 
264 
For assessee Firm (other than LLP), any field in A23 has any value "Have you exercised 
the option u/s 115BAC (6) of Opting out of new tax regime in Form 10-IEA in AY 2026-
27? "' 
265 
Under Schedule EI, Sl. No. iii Long term capital gains as per sec 112A are more than 
1,25,000 
266 
In Schedule EI, Sl. No. iii Long term capital gains as per sec 112A should be output of 
Sl. No. (i - ii) 
267 
Total income excluding LTCG u/s112A shall not be more than Rs. 50 Lakhs 
268 
In Part A General, Filing section is selected as 139(9) and the responses for A23 in 
139(9) do not match with the responses of A23 question in the ITR against which 
defective response is getting submitted. 
269 
"Details of Bank from which loan is taken" need to be provided for claiming Interest on 
borrowed capital u/s 24(b) in schedule Interest u/s 24(b) 
270 
Deduction u/s 80EE / 80EEA can be claimed when the limit u/s 24(b) is exhausted. 
271 
As the deduction u/s 80EE can be claimed over and above deduction u/s 24(b), "Details 
of bank from which loan is taken" in schedule 80EE should be part of the details 
disclosed in schedule 24(b) 
272 
As the deduction u/s 80EEA can be claimed over and above deduction u/s 24(b), "Details 
of bank from which loan is taken" in schedule 80EEA should be part of the details 
disclosed in schedule 24(b) 
273 
Details such as nature of payment, Amount eligible for deduction u/s 80C, Policy no. or 
Document Identification Number of supporting document are required to provide in 
schedule 80C to claim deduction 
274 
"Details of Bank from which loan is taken" need to be provided for claiming deduction 
u/s 80E in schedule 80E 
275 
"Details of Bank from which loan is taken" need to be provided for claiming deduction 
u/s 80EE in schedule 80EE 
276 
Deduction u/s 80EE can be claimed only if maximum loan taken does not exceed Rs. 35 
lakhs against the property 
277 
"Details of Bank from which loan is taken" needs to be provided for claiming deduction 
u/s 80EEA in schedule 80EEA 
278 
Deduction u/s 80EEA can be claimed only on the residential house property having 
stamp value up to Rs.45 Lakhs 
279 
The Date of sanction of loan under schedule 80EEA shall be between 1.4.19 and 31.3.22 
280 
"Details of Bank from which loan is taken" need to be provided for claiming deduction 
u/s 80EEB in schedule 80EEB 
281 
The Date of sanction of loan under schedule 80EEB shall be between 1.4.19 and 31.3.23 
282 
Details of Form 10BA are required to provide to claim deduction u/s 80GG 
283 
In schedule 80D, breakup of individual rows for "amount of premium paid" shall match 
with the Health insurance premium entered by the user under "Health insurance" at 
sl.no.1a 
284 
In schedule 80D, breakup of individual rows for "amount of premium paid" shall match 
with the Health insurance premium entered by the user under "Health insurance" at 
sl.no.1b 
285 
In schedule 80D, breakup of individual rows for "amount of premium paid" shall match 
with the Health insurance premium entered by the user under "Health insurance" at 
sl.no.2a 
286 
In schedule 80D, breakup of individual rows for "amount of premium paid" shall match 
with the Health insurance premium entered by the user under "Health insurance" at 
sl.no.2b 
287 
Form 10IA needs to be filed separately for claiming Deduction u/s 80U and 80DD, 
respectively. 

=== PAGE 18 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 18 
 
 
288 
Details of specified decrease are required to be provided to claim deduction u/s 80DDB 
289 
In schedule House property, value of “interest on borrowed capital" should be same as 
the "total of interest paid u/s 24(b)" as per schedule 24(b) 
290 
Deduction u/s 80C claimed under chapter VIA should be same as the “Total of payment 
made as per schedule 80C " 
291 
Deduction u/s 80E in schedule VIA should match with the "Total of interest paid" as per 
schedule 80E 
292 
Deduction u/s 80EE in schedule VIA should match with the "Total of interest paid" as 
per schedule 80EE 
293 
Deduction u/s 80EEA in schedule VIA should match with the "Total of interest paid" as 
per schedule 80EEA 
294 
Deduction u/s 80EEB in schedule VIA should match with the "Total of interest paid" as 
per schedule 80EEB 
295 
In schedule 24(b) the sum of individual rows for "Interest paid during the year" (x) shall 
match with the "Total of Payments" as per the schedule 24(b) 
296 
In schedule 80C the sum of individual rows for "Amount of payment" (ii) shall match 
with the "Total of Payments" as per the schedule 80C 
297 
In schedule 80E the sum of individual rows for "Amount of interest paid" (x) shall match 
with the "Total of Payments" as per the schedule 80E 
298 
In schedule 80EE the sum of individual rows for "Interest paid during the year" (x) shall 
match the "Total of Payments" as per the schedule 80EE 
299 
In schedule 80EEA the sum of individual rows for "Amount of interest paid" (ix) shall 
match with the "Total of Payments" as per the schedule 80EEA 
300 
In schedule 80EEB the sum of individual rows for "Amount of interest paid" (x) shall 
match with the "Total of Payments" as per the schedule 80EEB 
301 
The Date of sanction of loan In schedule 80EE shall be between 1.4.16 and 31.3.17 
302 
Interest on borrowed capital cannot be claimed in case of Self occupied house property 
under new tax regime 
303 
Assessee having status as Firm is not eligible to fill any schedule out of 80C Schedule, 
80E Schedule, 80EE Schedule, 80EEA Schedule, 80EEB Schedule or 10(13A) schedules 
for claiming respective deduction 
304 
Assessee having status as HUF is not eligible to fill any schedule out of 80CCC 
Schedule, 80E Schedule, 80EE Schedule, 80EEA Schedule or 80EEB Schedule for 
claiming respective deduction 
305 
Assessee having status as Individual and opting new tax regime have filled any of the 
schedules amongst 80C schedule, 80E schedule, 80EE schedule, 80EEA schedule, 
80EEB schedule or 10(13A) 
306 
Details such as name of the Insurer, Policy number, are required to be provided in 
schedule 80D to claim deduction for health insurance at sl. No. 1a (i) 
307 
Details such as name of the Insurer, Policy number are required to be provided in 
schedule 80D to claim deduction for health insurance at sl. No. 1b (i) 
308 
Details such as name of the Insurer, Policy number, and Receipt/document number of the 
premium paid are required to be provided in schedule 80D to claim deduction for health 
insurance at sl. No. 2a (i) 
309 
Details such as name of the Insurer, Policy number, are required to be provided in 
schedule 80D to claim deduction for health insurance at sl. No. 2b (i) 
310 
Section 192 applicable to Tax deducted on salary income is selected as the dropdown 
under schedule TDS 2(i), or 2(ii) which are for details of TDS on other than salary 
income. 
311 
HRA u/s 10(13A) shall not be more than Actual rent paid after deducting 10% of basic 
salary and DA 

=== PAGE 19 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 19 
 
 
312 
HRA u/s 10(13A) shall not be more than 50% of basic salary and DA  
313 
In schedule 10(13A) the lowest of the following amounts shall be claimed as HRA 
exemption: 
A) Actual HRA received 
B) Actual rent paid 10% of (salary+DA) 
C) 40% or 50% of (salary+DA) 
314 
Taxpayers having salary income and exempt allowances need to provide "Nature of 
employment" 
315 
"Schedule 10(13A) needs to be filled for claiming exempt allowance u/s 10(13A) 
316 
Sum of Basic salary, dearness allowance as per schedule 10(13A) and actual HRA 
received shall not be more than salary as per section 17(1) under Income details 
317 
Exempt allowance u/s 10(10)-Death-cum-retirement gratuity received cannot be more 
than 25,00,000 if nature of employment is "CG", "CG-Pensioners", "Sg" or "SG-
Pensioners" 
318 
Firm or HUF having date of formation on or after 01/04/2026 shall not be allowed to file 
return for AY 26-27 
319 
Status selected is Individual and having date of formation on or after 01/04/2008 shall 
not be allowed to file return for AY 25-26 
320 
Exempt Allowance u/s 10(13A) in schedule Salary should match with the "Eligible 
allowance u/s 10(13A)" as per schedule 10(13A) 
321 
Based on Response provided in A23, taxpayer shall response to the only one applicable 
question A23A or A23B. 
322 
Exempt Allowance "Exempt income received by a judge covered under the payment of 
salaries to Supreme Court/High Court judges Act /Rules" can be claimed only by CG/SG 
employees. 
323 
"Type of house property" shall be mandatory if interest on borrowed capital u/s 24(b) is 
claimed. 
324 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80C should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
325 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80CCC should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
326 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80CCD (1) should not be more than user 
enterable amount 
327 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80CCD(1B) should not be more than user 
enterable amount 
328 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80CCD (2) should not be more than user 
enterable amount 
329 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80D should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
330 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80DD should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
331 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80DDB should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
332 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80E should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
333 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80EE should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
334 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80EEA should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
335 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80EEB should not be more than user enterable 
amount 

=== PAGE 20 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 20 
 
 
336 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80G should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
337 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80GG should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
338 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80GGC should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
339 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80TTA should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
340 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80TTB should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
341 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80U should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
342 
Eligible amount of deduction claimed u/s 80CCH should not be more than user enterable 
amount 
343 
LTCG u/s 112A shall be equal to difference between GTI including LTCG and GTI 
excluding LTCG 
344 
In Part A General "Name of the representative, e-mail ID of the representative, Contact 
number of the representative" are mandatory if in Part- Verification capacity is selected 
as "Representative" from drop down 
345 
Whether this return is being filed by a representative assessee? Flag is Y then details 
should be provided 
346 
In case of Co-owned property, the total of assessee’ s share and co-owner's share should 
be equal to 100% 
347 
In Schedule HP, In case of co-owned property Annual value of the property owned 
should be own percentage share *Annual value. 
348 
Assessee share of co-owned property is zero then interest on borrowed capital cannot be 
more than zero', 
349 
In Schedule HP, Sl.no 1d -Total should be output of SL.no (1b+1c) 
350 
In Schedule HP, Sl.no 1i -Total should be output of SL.no (1g+1h) 
351 
In case of co-owned house property, Assessee PAN & Co-owners PAN cannot be same 
352 
Gross rent received/ receivable/ lettable value during the year is zero or null and "The 
amount of rent which cannot be realized" is more than 0 
353 
If A23" "Have you filed form 10IEA within due date for any earlier assessment year for 
choosing old tax regime? " is selected as "Yes” then (A)(i) and (A)(ii) shall be mandatory 
 
Note: Form 10IEA is required to be filed in case of business income so If you have filed 
form 10IEA within due date for any earlier assessment year along with ITR 3/4 then 
select "Yes". 
354 
If A23" "Have you filed form 10IEA within due date for any earlier assessment year for 
choosing old tax regime? " is selected as "No” then A23(B) shall be mandatory 
355 
If A23(A)(ii) "Have you filed ITR 3/4 in past and have re-entered new tax regime by 
filing form 10IEA for any assessment year subsequent to assessment year in which 
first form 10IEA was filed for choosing old tax regime?" 
is selected as "Yes" 
then it shall be mandatory to provide form 10IEA details under A23(A)(ii)(a) 
356 
If A23(A)(ii) "Have you filed ITR 3/4 in past and have re-entered new tax regime by 
filing form 10IEA for any assessment year subsequent to assessment year in which 
first form 10IEA was filed for choosing old tax regime?" 
is selected as "No" 
then  A23(A)(ii)(b) shall be mandatory  

=== PAGE 21 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 21 
 
 
357 
If A23(A)(ii)(b) "Have you furnished form 10IEA for re-entering in new tax regime in 
current assessment year?" 
is selected as "Yes" 
then it shall be mandatory to provide form 10IEA details under A23(A)(ii)(b)(i) 
358 
If A23(A)(ii)(b) "Have you furnished form 10IEA for re-entering in new tax regime in 
current assessment year?" 
is selected as "No" 
then A23(A)(ii)(b)(i) asking form filed details shall not be applicable 
359 
If A23(B) "Have you furnished form 10IEA within due date for current assessment year 
for choosing old tax regime?  
is selected as "Yes" 
 then A23(B)(i) shall be mandatory 
360 
If A23(B) "Have you furnished form 10IEA within due date for current assessment year 
for choosing old tax regime?  
is selected as "No" 
 then A23(B)(i) shall not be applicable 
361 
If form 10IEA details are filled in A23(B)(i) then A23(B) cannot be blank 
362 
If form 10IEA details are filled in A23(A)(ii)(b)(i) then A23(A)(ii)(b) cannot be blank 
363 
If Details are filled in A23 A(ii)(a) or A(ii)(b) then A23(A)(ii) cannot be blank 
364 
If Details are filled in A23 A(i) or A(ii) then A23(A) cannot be blank 
365 
Exempt Allowance "Exempt income received by a judge covered under the payment of 
salaries to Supreme Court/High Court judges Act /Rules" cannot be more than 0 if new 
tax regime is selected. 
366 
If in 80CCC the sum of individual rows for "Amount" is not equal to “Total of 
Payments" as per field 80CCC in Income details.  
367 
"Sec 10(2) Member’s share from HUF" drop-down cannot be selected more than one 
time under Exempt Income. 
368 
"Sec 10(10BB) payments made under the Bhopal Gas Leak Disaster" drop-down cannot 
be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
369 
"Sec 10(11A)- Sum received from an account opened under the Sukanya Samriddhi 
Yojan" drop-down cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
370 
"Sec 10(12A) NPS partial withdrawal" drop-down cannot be selected more than one time 
under Exempt Income. 
371 
"Sec 10(12AA) any payment from the National Pension System Trust" drop-down 
cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
372 
"Sec 10(12AB) any sum received as lump sum amount as per clause (vi) of paragraph 2 
of the notification number FX-1/3/2024-PR" drop-down cannot be selected more than 
one time under Exempt Income. 
373 
"Sec 10(12B) NPS lumpsum at exit/closure (portion)" drop-down cannot be selected 
more than one time under Exempt Income. 
374 
"Sec 10(12BA) partial withdrawal made from the National Pension System" drop-down 
cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
375 
"Sec 10(12C) Agniveer Corpus Fund income" drop-down cannot be selected more than 
one time under Exempt Income. 
376 
"Sec 10(15) Interest on specified securities/investments" drop-down cannot be selected 
more than one time under Exempt Income. 
377 
"Sec 10(19A) Annual value of one palace in occupation of ex-ruler" drop-down cannot 
be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
378 
"Sec 10(23AA) Sum received by any person on behalf of any Fund established by the 
armed force" drop-down cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 

=== PAGE 22 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 22 
 
 
379 
"Contributions received from recognized stock exchange" drop-down cannot be selected 
more than one time under Exempt Income. 
380 
"Sec 10(23FBB)-income referred to in section 115UB, accruing or arising to, or received 
by, a unit holder of an investment fund” drop-down cannot be selected more than one 
time under Exempt Income. 
381 
"Sec 10(23FD) Unit holder income from Business Trust (certain parts" drop-down 
cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
382 
"Sec 10(25)-Sum received by trustees on behalf of approved superannuation, gratuity, or 
pension fund" drop-down cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
383 
"Sec 10(25A) any income under Employees' State Insurance Fund" drops down cannot 
be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
384 
"Sec 10(30) subsidy received from or through the Tea Board" drop-down cannot be 
selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
385 
"Sec 10(31) Rubber/Coffee/Tea development accounts/funds" drop-down cannot be 
selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
386 
"Minor child’s income—small exemption" drop-down cannot be selected more than one 
time under Exempt Income. 
387 
"Sec 10(35) Income from specified Mutual Funds" drop-down cannot be selected more 
than one time under Exempt Income. 
388 
"Sec 10(35A) distributed income referred to in section 115TA received from a 
securitization trust" drop-down cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt 
Income. 
389 
"Sec 10(43) Reverse mortgage—payments to senior citizens" drop-down cannot be 
selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
390 
"Sec 10(44) Income received by any person for, or on behalf of, the New Pension System 
Trusts" drop-down cannot be selected more than one time under Exempt Income. 
391 
If New tax regime is selected, then exempt income u/s 10(32)-Minor child’s income 
should not be more than Zero 
392 
Fees for furnishing revised return under 234-I shall be equal to Rs. 1000 if ITR is filed 
after 31/12/2026 and filing section is 139(5) and total income does not exceed 5lakh Rs. 
393 
The AY selected in A23(A)(ii)(a) shall not be same or prior to the AY selected in 
A23(A)(i) 
For e.g.: AY selected in A23(A)(i) is AY 2024-25 
then AY selected in A23(A)(ii)(a) shall not be same as AY 2024-25 or 
prior to AY2024-25 but can be any AY greater than AY 2024-25 
394 
IFSC and "Transaction Reference number for _UPI transfer / Cheque 
number/IMPS/NEFT/RTGS reference number,” in Schedule 80G is mandatory in case of 
donation is in mode other than cash. 
395 
PAN of donee shall be mandatory in case donation amount is more than 0 in schedule 
80G 
396 
If Old Tax Regime is selected, 
 and In "schedule 80G" if multiple entries are there under donation in cash with same 
PAN, then if sum of such cash donation does not exceed Rs. 2000 then eligible amount 
of donation shall not exceed minimum of: 
Rs. 2000 or  
claimed whichever is lower 
397 
Fees for furnishing revised return under 234-I shall be equal to Rs. 5000 if ITR is filed 
after 31/12/2026 and filing section is 139(5) and total income exceeds 5lakh Rs. 
398 
Name and PAN of the political party are necessary to claim deduction u/s 80GGC 
399 
In Schedule 80G either cash donation or donation in other mode shall be entered under 
any row; both can’t be entered. 
402 
PRAN should be provided in schedule VIA to claim deduction u/s 80CCD(1), or 

=== PAGE 23 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 23 
 
 
80CCD(1B) 
403 
In Part A General, Email id and contact no of the representative assessee should not 
match with Email id (primary and secondary) and contact no (primary and secondary) of 
taxpayer. 
404 
In case of property is not Co-owned the assessee's share should be equal to 100% 
405 
In Schedule HP, if "Is property co-owned" is selected as Yes, then Percentage share of 
other co-owner(s) in property should be greater than 0 and less than 100% 
406 
In Schedule HP, if "Is property co-owned" is selected as Yes, then Assessee’s percentage 
of share in the Property (%) should be less than 100% 
407 
If PRAN is entered in chapter VIA but amount entered in 80CCD (1) and 80CCD(1B) is 
equal to 0 
408 
"The amount of rent which cannot be realized" cannot be more than Gross rent received/ 
receivable/ lettable during the year 
409 
If Deduction u/s 80CCC is more than 0 then it shall be mandatory to add at least one row 
and provide details for "Type of identifier", "Identifier No. and "Amount" 
410 
Secondary Address in Schedule Part A General Information is mandatory to be provided 
in the return of income 
411 
Secondary address should not be same as Primary address if "No" is mentioned for "Is 
the secondary address same as primary address?" in Schedule Part A General 
Information 
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
2.2 
Category B: 
 
Table 3: Category B Rules 
 
Sl. No. 
Publishing Document 
1 
Income chargeable under business should be equal to sum of income offered under 
presumptive income under 44AD, 44ADA & 44AE 
2 
TDS deducted value in schedule TDS 1 CANNOT BE MORE THAN value in 
schedule Salary "sl.no.2. Total Gross salary"  
3 
Linking of Aadhar and PAN is required to avoid consequences of not linking PAN 
and Aadhar in eligible cases as per Circular 03/2023 
4 
Quoting of Aadhar in ITR is required as per section 139(AA)in applicable cases and 
also linking of Aadhar and PAN is required to avoid consequences of not linking 
PAN and Aadhar in eligible cases as per Circular 03/2023 
5 
Taxpayer filing Nil return is requested to check AIS / 26AS before proceeding 
further 
6 
TDS section code such 194B, 194BB, 194BA,194IA,194IC,194LA,or 194S as is 
selected under Schedule "TDS2(i) Details of Tax Deducted at Source on Income 
Other than Salary" at field 2a "Section under which TDS deducted" 
or 
Assessee having income under special rate is not eligible to file ITR-4. 
7 
TDS section code such 194B, 194BB, 194BA, 194IA,194IC,194LA,194R, or 194S 
as is selected under Schedule "TDS2(ii) Details of Tax Deducted at Source on 
Income Other than Salary" at field 2a "Section under which TDS deducted" 
or 
Assessee having income under special rate is not eligible to file ITR-4. 

=== PAGE 24 ===
CBDT_e-Filing_ITR 4_Validation Rules for AY 2026-27 
V 1.0 
Page 24 
 
 
8 
TDS section code such as 
194E,194LB,194LC,194LBA(a),194LBA(b),194LBA©,195,196A,196B,196C,196D 
or 196D(1A) is selected under Schedule "TDS2(i) Details of Tax Deducted at 
Source on Income Other than Salary" at field 2a "Section under which TDS 
deducted" 
9 
TDS section code such as 
194E,194LB,194LC,194LBA(a),194LBA(b),194LBA©,195,196A,196B,196C,196D 
or 196D(1A) is selected under Schedule "TDS2(ii) Details of Tax Deducted at 
Source on Income Other than Salary" at field 2a "Section under which TDS 
deducted" 
10 
If form 10IEA is available in the DB then the below fields shall be mandatory to be 
filled for the respective AY and the details entered shall be matching with the DB : 
Assessment year, 
Date of filing form 10IEA or 
Acknowledgement number of form 10-IEA 
11 
Form 10IEA shall be filed within the due date for opting out or re-entering for the 
current assessment year 
12 
Form 10IEA is not filed previously but the details are entered in the ITR. 
13 
Form 10IEA is not filed for the current assessment year but the details are entered in 
the ITR.  
 
2.3 
Category D: 
 
Table 4: Category D Rules 
 
Sl. No.  
Publishing Document 
1.  
The assessee has claimed relief u/s 89(1) without furnishing of Form 10E 
2.  
Deduction u/s 80GG can be claimed only upto 5000 per month (maximum 12 months) or 
the rent actually paid, whichever is lower." 
 
 
 

